[Music]
the cognitive complexity of issues that
the world faces is more than a single
person can process single brain that
can't actually hold that cognitive
complexity so it requires collective
intelligence and collective sense we're
probably not going to solve the complex
we give existential problems we face
with individual horsepower of thing
rivalries games we're probably going to
need to get together and be able to
create a higher form of collective
intelligence and sense making now what
and how so the answer now what is
decentralize collective intelligence
great how how do we do that
[Music]
honest I'm kind of interesting hearing
your narrative on why sense-making is
important why this question and I'm not
actually gonna name the question yet
whatever the question is why it is not
just important but central what I think
the strange attractor that draws us all
here together is sense-making
it's about the exploration into what is
real and what is meaningful is bound to
what's real and we find that we have the
at least have the experience of having
choice and we're trying to find out how
to orient our choice and so since making
to inform choice making is what is what
is reality what is my relationship with
reality what is fundamentally meaningful
as a basis for how I can make choices
that are more aligned with what I find
meaningful
yeah my think mine's probably many
layers of abstraction below these
framings although a totally you know
track and appreciate what you guys are
also saying my basic gut senses hey back
to complicated versus complex we're
probably not going to solve the complex
we could existential problems we face
with individual horsepower playing
rivalries games we're probably going to
need to get together and be able to
create a higher form of collective
intelligence and sense making and what
I've been seeing lately paying attention
to this space is it's starting to bubble
up but it feels like a wildly unstable
element and it's breaking my heart /
freaking me out
it's not concerning me that we our
efforts to create group coherent seem to
be going so badly so far and so I'm
deeply committed to figuring out what
are the rate limiters / Achilles heels
missing links that can help us at least
stop you know failing forward making you
better different mistakes because it
feels like our efforts right now are
actually just the last half century red
ducks with very little go forward
learning happening so it feels like
transformational culture is basically
just repeating the baby boomer hippie
new-age traps and just running into the
running off the roads at exactly all the
same places there's already the skid
marks and so talking with you guys I
find incredibly valuable on what are the
big systemic issues what are other ways
to think of this and how do we help give
more people in your terms the generator
functions to keep figuring this up
together and make newer better more
suspect
there is just not the same hole I heard
ridiculous I mean my my patter I think
is the in fact it may be identical but
my experience of it of the way I would
even describe is very first person which
is that my path here is through a very
very large number of distinct personal
failures like just running into a wall
and going okay well that's wrong turning
a little bit bring into another wall
that's wrong turning a little bit right
into another wall ik the number of times
that I have up is insane like I
came in like thousands if not tens of
thousands it's crazy and in the process
of that for example this is a good case
study one of the things they ended up
getting a hold it was the notion that
you could actually do things when you
could imagine what the consequences of
your actions might be quite a distance
down the road and you could actually
really really good at that to the point
you could actually sit there and hear
someone to describe a plan to you and
you could listen to the plan and go that
won't work right and be very confident
that in fact that plan is not a good
plan I mean an example might be I'm
going to walk up to the fireplace and
point my hands I didn't say light I'll
say well you know that's not gonna work
I've got a good model of how reality
works I've done this sort of thing
before bad plan alright so what I found
though was that as I absorb more and
more life experience and more and more
knowledge I began to be noticed that
more and more often more and more
people's plans were of that sort
and that was like well that's
interesting so I took that as an object
of inquiry and by the way again my own
being first and foremost so okay
long-term planning is not working out so
I got you know kept going okay how can
you actually make effective choices how
can you actually plan at all
about what's gonna happen in the future
and what I began to notice was the stuff
we've been talking about like everything
that we currently believe that we can
plan won't work like none of the stuff
that we have in our tool kit that allows
us to make plans for the future is gonna
work out fill in the blank like pick any
problem I kept running the situations
when people describe a particular
problem everything we're gonna solve
climate we're gonna solve conflict we're
gonna solve education
just listen to them talk about their
plan and go well that's not gonna work
only is that not gonna work it's gonna
work like terribly what's happening so
this led me to then finally looking at
it okay what might and then that began
the process of saying okay how do we
actually get to the point we can begin
to get some level of clarity on what
might actually be a meaningful step and
that leads me here that this is the
answer to that question the answer of
recognizing that the question of sense
making together is ultimately a question
of how do I make better choices and how
do I and you become a we who make better
choices hopefully in some context that
builds to us collectively actually being
able to make the kinds of better choices
that are truly responsive to the
environment we find ourselves in like
it's just sort of the first step of that
cycle
[Music]
the way I've been describing it is I do
it in a historical narrative which is to
say that there was a method of human
beings coming together into a group that
had certain adaptive capacities that I'm
gonna call the the Dunbar coherence and
this is what we've talked about it's
like that thing that happened somewhere
around the Paleolithic transition the
Upper Paleolithic transition where
humans suddenly kicked into something
that was kind of a new thing culture the
human animal began to kick ass I'm gonna
call that the Dunbar coherence and that
was really effective and that blew all
over the world humanity covered the
whole globe filled every niche became
the people in every niche until
somewhere in the range of 35,000 ish
years ago it started running into itself
it was able to out-compete every other
organism on the planet until it ran into
itself and so when humans from the dim
bar coherence ran into other humans were
in the Dunbar coherence and they were so
successful that their population began
rising beyond the carrying capacity the
environment that they're in ie they
entered into self created conditions of
real scarcity then they had to start
competing with each other and this led
to a next wave of evolutionary
exploration for trying to find something
that was a more effective way for human
beings to come together and work
together than the Dunbar coherence
that's game a game a is a solution to
the problem of how do you get people to
be able to work together effectively as
a group at scale and so Dunbar what the
limitation of the Dunbar coherence was
that it couldn't scale past 150 people
so a rock Harare posits basically he
reduces it all massively and says it's
our ability to gossip I don't think
that's that reductio was really bad in
my perspective it's a lot of stuff like
our ability to embody models of other
people's states and the state of all the
complementary relationships they have
there's an example like there's a lot of
stuff going on many of it
game a this is all right how do I
solved the problem of scale while
maintaining the benefits of people
working together and this is the three
problems how do I actually create
something where the group is effectively
able to actually support itself in the
context of nature how do I create a
condition where it doesn't eat itself
from the inside how do I avoid
corruption infection and things like
that and how do I actually create enough
power inside that that group that it can
actually compete now with other groups
now of course we had the whole story of
game a playing out over time the
solution the game a comes up with is
this entire store there's society mind
paradigms so think of it as like a most
computational actuation that simplifies
human relationships and puts them in
very simple relationships to have inputs
and outputs formal structures money law
anything that can fit in a semantic
narrative the actually have been really
held by a person in teaching if you've
written down in a book and repeat it
over and over again it's simplified
there's a lot to it but I want to mean
we don't have forever so then we fast
forward it's okay game a has a whole
bunch of things inside as possibility
space so it can we deliver on the Ming
Dynasty and Rome and the Prussians and
21st century us sorry these are all
inside the thing the game they can be
but they're all variations on that theme
we come to where we are now the problems
that we're facing or a different set of
problems right and the problems we run
into now is that game a in and of itself
can't ultimately deal with complexity
both complexity in terms of actually
being able to take full closed-loop
responsibility for the for the national
environment every instantiation of game
a that has ever shown up has always
ultimately depleted the resources of the
environment that is sitting on top of to
a level of collapse of some sort
couldn't feed enough people either
produced you too many people or depleted
the resources it can't deal with
complexity on the inside meaning that it
always goes through some kind of group
selection on the interior corruption
defection dynamic that leads to
fragility that causes it to collapse on
the outside and then the third is the
thing that we talked about which is that
precisely because it is so effective at
power on an underlying premise of
win-lose dynamics
was invented for the purpose of
competing with other people in the
context of scarcity as it actually has
become extremely powerful this is the
problem becoming godlike at the level of
power but not at the level of wisdom
right so a game a runs to the limits of
its of its boundary conditions it can't
solve those three fundamental problems
in Evin of itself so something new has
to be developed so it's okay well that's
game B just literally we're just
defining a place it's a pointer to
something over here so like a wool what
is that the first thing is the reason
why we can name it game B is to say
what's something that is in fact a
different game altogether all right so
go over to the basis it's something on
the order of magnitude of the difference
between the band level nomadic Dunbar
150 human level and every single thing
that has happened in civilization since
then that whole box is different right
that order of magnitude and it has
characteristics that allow it to
actually actually address these three
questions and their complexity natural
complexity and the problematic of
exponential technology that comes from
learning it's okay
what does that look like what are some
characteristics of that and that's some
of the things we've been talking about
today at the center of it for me at
least as I've gone through the
questioning of this over and over and
over again it recognized for example
that you have to change the mind
otherwise you just recapitulate this
society is this thing we've been calling
coherent collective intelligence and
coherence specifically is that the very
center of it but in many ways game be
even talked about has a bit of that
Taoist sense to it as you're naming it
in the context of game a quite often
you're actually importing gaming into it
so you have to actually treat it very
very carefully it's less about being
able to describe it than it is in fact
just being able to do it it is the kind
of thing that you do not the kind of
thing you talk about you can talk about
how you can become capable of it but
designing it talking about it is
generally a full fundamental error that
does that make sense what I'm saying
there
I mean I think just depends on how
taoist we imagine game B to be well
that's very odd because you can't
actually be Taoist interesting enough
but it can actually be it's more like
the Taoist insight that points to the
Dao I can say very clearly if I could
articulate it my definition is
complicated it's not complicated game B
is not complicated game B must be
intrinsically complex so I cannot define
it in any finite set of statements
because any finite set of statements
it's complicated so it's not that kind
of thing so if I'm explaining as I'm
describing it I have to be doing it in
something which is essentially poetic
not a specification or where as daniel
said I'm pointing towards the generator
functions they give rise to something
that is more than the thing that is said
noticing three distinct things to come
up one is the question of why why did
this thing which I'll just call
coherence that we've been talking about
the the second is why does it thus far
fail to scale and then of course the
third is how might we do about solving
that problem all three seem to be
showing up close to each other in my
sense do you want to share more what you
mean by coherence all right immediately
what comes up so what is this thing and
there's a lot of different ways of
talking about it but we might say
there's ah actually interesting it seems
like you actually have to talk about it
in many different ways because it is the
kind of thing that cannot be conveyed
effectively in language you know it's
the matrix unfortunately no one can be
told what coherence is but we can't
actually tell a lot of different stories
it's become the blonde with the elephant
and after a little while we
might be able to in ourselves grass
perhaps what is being pointed out so one
way of describing it is it is a it's a
form of collective intelligence that has
as a characteristic a high degree of
capacity in the space of novelty and a
intrinsic antifragility in both human
and throw Powe complexity and nature
complexity another way of saying that is
if you work backwards in taking a look
at all the different challenges and
problems that we are currently facing we
meaning humanity is the answer to the
set that contains those problems another
way of describing it is it's something
like flow since we have that as a nice
concrete frame then we can invoke that
in an unconstrained way ie we oftentimes
associate with flow with flow in a
domain a rock-climber isn't flowing
climbing rocks a jazz band isn't flow
and playing jazz coherence is flow
absent context absent a particular
application you know so
mentioned he said it has a relationship
with novelty what prompts you to put
that into the mix because if I just hear
the word coherent so that just feels let
you know from physics electronics
whatever it would just be things in some
form of sync with each other but you
added in novelty and antifragility the
brothers have seemed interesting but
they're not what I would have just
expected to come from the word so can
you help unpack either the Y or the how
you got to those yeah I think also to
begin it's I think what you bring up is
good we should just say that there's
different kinds of collective
intelligence and some kinds of
collective intelligence we have
different names for with my call them
different things so in this context
we're going to have to be very familiar
with the notion that word choice is
oftentimes going to require some careful
definition as you just did so let's just
for everyone who's listening just
recognize that oftentimes I have a
certain vocabulary daniel has vocabulary
you have a vocabulary we're all
operating under what I've called rule
Omega which is listen to what is being
expressed not what is being said and
asked good questions until what is being
expressed has actually felt it's landed
so if we think about the examples of
flow you've provided so well one of the
things that shows up so commonly is a
sense of there being an emergence or a
synergy where there's something about a
hole that is greater than the sum of the
parts and that as it turns out happens
to be the best way to respond to novelty
let me add some words that I think might
add clarity to a question I hear you
asking we've discussed offline some
different types of coherence in
different contexts and like formal
models for looking at what coherence in
different contexts means and so when you
mention like physics like things of the
same type
like pendulums or lasers that's a
coherence of sameness they all become
the same wavelength
they have the same periodicity and when
we're talking about humans being able to
come into coherence we're not wanting a
homogenizing coherence and if you think
about something like a body liver cells
and neurons and fat cells are all very
different types of cells and yet they're
operating in a way where the body is an
emergent property that has capacities
that none of the cells or organs or
subsystems they can separately have so
it's a coherence of different things
where the difference is the basis of
synergy rather than being the basis of
an unreconciled or conflict the
difference is a basis for synergy where
each of them have capacity separately
and then the whole has capacities
neither of them have that are found in
each of them plus the relationships as
opposed to the differences being a basis
for unreconciled will conflict so we're
interested here in the types of
coherence that can occur where there are
differences right differences of
experience differences of perspective
and yet like so I'll just tie a couple
other words together Jordan said he said
it's kind of like flow if we think of
flow from fluid dynamics in terms of
like laminar flow versus turbulent flow
there's a more flow is less entropy and
actually not just less entropy buts
entropy the movement towards holes that
have greater than some of the parts and
so I think that's what we're really
interested in collective sense making is
how do we come together in relationship
that has less friction less entropy
relationally Moore's entropy where the
group of us has capacities has emergent
properties that aren't found in any of
us in isolation the coherence is that
phenomena that emergent properties arise
from right and then so the the other
distinction was we've got we've got
examples of this kind that have no we're
actually gonna get pretty nuanced so we
may as well just be careful about the
were getting nuanced we have a
particular kind of coherence I'm just
gonna label coordination just we have a
label for it and this has a lot of weird
Angels talking about in fact it has
emergent properties so for example if
you've got a mathematician having a
conversation with an economist there's
in fact a hole in their conversation
that is greater than the sum of the
parts there's there's a connection
between those two ways of thinking the
toolkits of mathematics that's not
available as the economist unlocks
things the economist wouldn't have known
about but for example the economists
questions that weren't things the
mathematician was thinking about unlocks
things the mathematician wasn't thinking
about right so there's a synergy value
to that that's also not the thing we're
talking about that's awesome
really good useful but for very specific
reasons which we can go to if we'd like
it doesn't actually have the capacity to
to satisfy the requirements of call it
the problems that we're facing Kant said
if I just satisfy the problems of nature
natural complexity it can't satisfy the
problems event ropo complexity one of
which is why it keeps breaking down
every time you try to build something
like this an trope of complexity often
times it becomes the primary reason why
it breaks down yeah I mean it seems like
if I'm hearing right the question is
just how how can we get together with
each other in a way that leaves us
smarter kind of more creative more
courageous more resilient
than any of us are a part and me at
least as far as terms for me flow is
often a bit of a buzzword and I think a
lot of people project onto it but some
slightly more precise like if I'm
thinking of examples and you can tell me
if I'm barking up the right tree or not
but like examples I think of is Victor
Turner's notion at University of Chicago
community toss which is a it's not
simply a collection it's not just a
crowd or a mom it's a felt presence of
coherence among a group and then you
think about like Quakers use the term a
gathered meeting there's a regular
meeting we all shuffle into the meeting
house no one says much and and people or
even people may say a few things and
that can not be a gathered meeting
that's just a physical collection of
humans on a Sunday morning but a
gathered meeting is there you know over
centuries of really delicate listening
into that is that place where you're
speaking only when spoken through and
that the collective intelligence is
given voice through a given individual
but it's clearly not just their thoughts
ideas or words does that try yes for you
guys okay
now I know obviously analogies of humans
and brains and minds to computers are
obviously problematic and a whole bunch
of different levels but as far as a
simple one does this also seem to be the
notion of connecting CPUs or computers
in serial such that the connected
computational power and capacity is
greater than any of the things in
between and that they might actually
even be able to tackle problems that in
any individual computer would be
uncapable of solving actually no and
that goes back to the in addition of
coordination so that style of connection
is coordination and it does have the
characteristic of increasing capacity
and in fact increasing capacity in a
fashion that is
well at least depending on the specific
kind of problem and the physical
capacity to do compute often times it
better to polish if you're solving
particular kinds of problems that make
sense so much of sin it doesn't I'm just
winning is there a magic in the
supercomputer is there a like for
instance if all I can do is let's go
back 20 years you know and if all I
could do is do email and AOL you know
but if we connected up enough of them
together we can actually project a
hologram and actually you know model
something totally new and different but
none of those things couldn't do i mean
if it's if it's a problematic metaphor
we can abandoned i'm just thinking no
it's a big it's a very good metaphor and
problematic
you don't wanna ban it it we actually
want to have it be helpful leave
double-click on why yeah there are
elements of parallel processing and
elements of serial processing that are
important and then there's something
that can't be fully contained in
parallel and serial and the thing that i
am sensing jordan's calling coherence is
what is our we do we have a model where
we're reducing consciousness to
computation and if not what
consciousness is other than computation
as part of the limits of that model
yeah i don't know where this comes from
but i think it might be yeah Union
analysis perhaps but the notion of the
third they talked about in like dyadic
relationships and sometimes they'll even
do couples therapy whether it's almost
like you know a plate for Elijah or you
know like you see for Elvis it's like
there's the third and the third is the
intelligence of the relationship and is
the third you know a working place the
idea that there is between an among us
but not specific to any of us an
additional intelligence that can emerge
and that is that that is that the
differentiator between what you were
describing is coherence and simply maybe
collective intelligence or proper
coordination your coordination yep okay
very I'm gonna say yes okay yeah and so
I'm wanting to translate different
ontology listeners might be coming from
and say there's a couple at least a
couple different ways we can think about
this both of which are meaningful
so there's a question of can we come
into a type of relationship as beings
where there is a kind of synergy a kind
of coherence where there's actually an
emergent property of something antek
that then has a top-down effect in us we
can actually listen to that and there's
some interesting kind of metaphysical
propositions that would make that be the
case and I would say that's interesting
and then there's also the well if that's
not true and mine is still processing in
separate brains is there still something
we're intending to listen in to the
group as opposed to just myself and just
having the intention to consider the
perspectives of everyone there consider
the relationships between everyone there
consider the group as a whole not just
the individuals and the individuals and
speak what could be relevant and useful
for everyone and feel think about that
and feel into it use your whole self I
don't have to have a ontology of an
emergent collective consciousness to
have that process be a useful thing so
is there a point Jordan is is it helpful
or problematic to consider so let's say
what you just said which is let's call
it super skillful active Collective
listening right where it's it you can
take first person second person third
person perspectives fluidly in order to
help both you know articulate it extract
make sense of as much information and
sense making as we can together that
feels sort of secular humanist rational
that's just us being better people
playing better together is there
anything - what is gained and lost by
positing the third positing a
transpersonal element that may even
render us our individuality sub ordinate
- so clearly right so so in a lot of
traditional societies they might have
some wild-ass crazy ritual
well like you know Haitian Vodou nor
something like that and there may be the
there is a God or a spirit that this
ritual is dedicated to and when enough
of us lose our separate sin itself they
would have they would tell the story or
make the meaning that that is when the
spirit of such-and-such has come through
right if we're talking about post
rational coherence is there a thing that
is super ordinate to us if so is that
helpful in the sense of like get out of
the way
all right we're landing the mothership
or is it problematic because it creates
magical thinking projections and other
stuff well interestingly I think we
actually have a nice self referentiality
that just happens right here because so
the first step might be something like
something I call a paradigm mapping and
Daniel actually did paradigm that many
moment ago so you take a particular
story that somebody's telling and you
point by point map it to a particular
paradigm so I could describe that in
terms of cognitive science and say okay
what's really happening is that when we
create a proposition that there's a
third what this does in our own minds is
that it allows us to no longer have an
emotional attachment to the rightness or
the wrongness a particular idea which
gives rise to a cognitive capacity to be
more creative more fluid in explorations
and therefore is a more generative way
it's a it's a form of hack that allows
us to have that cognitive disposition
right so I just did a mapping to a kind
of language in cognitive science that
would take somebody who loads and runs
cognitive science as a sense making
framework and make them go okay that
makes sense feels good my I don't feel
scared or angry about what's happening
right now that feels like a feasible
thing but of course the meta proposition
is that mapping it to a paradigm full
stop at all is the problem so anytime
you're actually trying to make sense by
mapping to a paradigm whether the
paradigm is a you know Vishnu or the God
pan or cognitive neuroscience or
whatever you're already recapturing the
discourse
in a particular way of thinking that
limits its capacity to be the thing
we're trying to actually do so the
answer to the question is like if the
answer the question like the classic
Buddhists just whack you in the back of
the head like that's the only real
response to that kind of a question is
don't go that direction
sure okay so so yes and then but he so
if coherence is this ephemeral emergent
property the best never named the never
subject to reality captured reality
tunnel capture like it's that thing then
how the hell do skill it cuz we're
storytelling monkeys and at some point
we need recipes to help the thing
propagate so this good unless
everybody's job Yodas then why does it
always break down mm-hmm why do why are
we to meet we just go doesn't break down
one of the reasons is because as our
friend Lao Tzu discovered and by the way
also a friend Buddha discovered enter
friend Jesus discovered every time the
storytelling monkeys try to turn to a
story to tell they it up
so let's be mindful of that and
recognize that the storytelling piece of
it definitely isn't the answer
okay so Sherlock Holmes style now carve
that out of the available portfolio of
things that we can do how do we go about
doing anything at all that doesn't
involve being a storytelling monkey okay
we've got it we've got an arrow problem
it's it's smaller it's a smaller space
but you know so let's just think I mean
if you know where we are culturally
these days there's a lot of people are
stumbling into these spaces via broad
access to ecstatic technologies so
whether that's transformational ffedith
festivals or you know transformational
technologies or whatever it is or
psychopharmacology you know all these
things people are bumbling into these
spaces on purpose or not they're getting
there they're recognizing holy
we're in the deep end and or this is rad
this is awesome this is terrifying this
is powerful right whatever it will be
they they're they know it when they're
getting there even if they're not a
hundred percent sure
how they got there and then the moment
they're no longer in that coherent field
we're back to trying to make sense of it
in the prison-house of language telling
stories and making analogies or
metaphors so let's take a distinction I
think we this distinction I think is
quite helpful there's at least two
distinct uses of language this one over
here
I'll call semantic reality mapping this
is really good for things like building
houses or putting together battle plans
it Orient's coordinated behavior where
the checksum of reality is pretty strong
science does a lot of this science is
pretty much this kind of thing over here
is poetry parable where the fingers
pointing to the moon and the point is
the moon not the finger this we can use
we're just to be very careful that we're
not doing this so the problem that I
think happens all the time
particular with the folks that wear lots
of feathers and like to take too many
drugs is they do this so they have an
experience and then try to turn to
science so pre-scripted versus
descriptive both really they do
prescription and description because
poetry is not really description it's an
octave figurative versus literal yes
yeah so the trick is we have to actually
be able to use language is some way of
creating a resonance frequency or
protocol match that generates a capacity
for communication that is not itself
specifically semantic which I would
propose both parable and poetry do it
Orient's you in the direction of a
feeling in yourself like think about
poetry when you read a poem you don't
understand the poem but there's
something about the way that the poem
coordinates language helps you weren't
in yourself to an experience that feels
like the feeling that the poet was also
feeling
and so it creates a possibility of there
being a connection at the level of
interior feeling not a connection at the
level of understanding
well something something you're I mean
it felt like you did have some future
forward practicality and application in
your initial description you said it
does well with novelty and it's anti
fragile and there's me as you thought of
it feel like timeless qualities but it
for sure feels important now and going
forward and and I was wondering because
if we can't do the here's the
instructions on how to get back here
because then we've named a thing that's
not the thing
and emergent coherence is kind of this
weird slippery thing to pin down you
have communities of practice like
Quakers and others that have spent
centuries and even you know generations
passing on that knowledge I was just
with some indigenous for DNA and Lakota
folks right and they have an infinite
tradition of we will talk until the
thing that needed to get done emerges
but nor are we on the clock and if this
takes ten minutes so be it if this takes
10 days so be it so is there a version
of this that is you know kind of
quote-unquote scalable in the 21st
century for our current situations and
conditions and also nervous systems and
time scales / distract abilities or are
those incompatible and we actually need
to say if you humans groups of humans
care about the possibility space that
coherence might afford us then you're
going to need to unplug and have a
different value set than contemporary
mainstream norms and
bit rates cominius is pretty simple if
somebody says they want to become a to
play basketball for in for the for the
Lakers they probably ought to become a
really good basketball player I mean the
real answer is that these lineage
traditions indicate to us that the human
instrument has a particular ambient
capacity to achieve of things this thing
coherent okay our job is to get really
really good at that to take that
particular ami in capacity and hone it
to a level that is the equivalent of a
contemporary marathon runner or a
contemporary sprinter honing the
instrument of running in a way that a
stone-age human can't become the Usain
Bolt of coherence is the answer to the
question it's there it's clearly
possible you're not becoming Usain Bolt
though remember once the five-minute
mile was at the five-minute mile the
three minute mile four-minute mile once
the four-minute mile was broken which
was considered to be impossible now
you've got high school students who can
do it and it says one of those things
where once you actually get your
particular node there's a possible this
is a location the possibility space of
homo sapiens sapiens but can actually
achieve that particular point get there
and then build this the tech name of
that and bring other people into that
place and use that to discover how to
actually scale it here I think you're
asking very important and also the
hardest questions and we don't have some
of the previous structures together yet
that we would deem through so when you
talk about how would we have a kind of
coherence of collective sense making and
collective choice making at scale well
we've never had at that scale right as
you're mentioning there was a certain
level that some tribes were able to
develop it was part of how tribal life
happened and we know that below Dunbar
number and above done row number there's
really fundamental
and then number is not a number it's
arranged based on the level of coherence
of the type of people more coherence
better communication protocols slightly
bigger number but one way of thinking
about the Dunbar number is a level at
which the communication protocols that
mediate the coherence break down which
is what you're asking a scale question
as you mentioned we'll talk it out if it
takes 10 days if I've got less than 150
people say and there's a big decision
that's gonna affect everybody's life
everyone can actually enter a tribal
conversation and all get to be part of
something that's gonna affect them which
means everyone sense-making can be held
together this was your question around
parallel and series right it's like both
those everybody sense making can be
heard and then choice making can factor
everybody sense making but if I met
thousands of people there's no way to
have everybody talk to even hear each
other without some kind of technology -
and so then tribes got bigger than that
by certain kinds of evolutionary forcing
functions by instituting things like
command and control hierarchy that
controlled the communication flows where
some people were doing choice making not
informed by the sense making of the
whole and now you get diminishing
returns on collective intelligence and
that's been the only scaling methods
we've had and that was that angry gods
hypothesis thing that we were sure yeah
there's many different technologies for
maintaining that particular style of
collective intelligence which of course
I could - is called game a like a whole
whole way of solving that problem yeah
basically game a and scaling
coordination or that are pretty
synonymous scaling coordination beyond
the Dunbar number huh meaning all the
other additional bells and whistles of
game a you would you would assert
basically I kind of follow on for how do
you how do you control and coordinate
resources and humans beyond 100 250 yeah
yeah money formal hierarchy the notion
of formality in general the idea that
there's a role that somebody fills as
opposed to humans are just humans and
sometimes like that minute from formal
subordination to dynamic subordination
that shift
law policing each one of these are just
tools in the gaming a toolkit that are
all endeavoring to solve that problem
shared n group identity like political
left or nationality or religion or race
or whatever this allows a coordination
of an in-group relative to an out group
in an assumed rival risk context and so
game a is basically rival risk game
theory there's a way of stating it and
sort of it has three distinct challenges
that it's always trying to solve for
it's trying to solve for is it able to
coordinate so as to maintain the
integrity of the whole in the context of
nature get it feed everybody is it able
to coordinate in the context of each
other its able to avoid defection or
group selection inside its interior or
just corruption and is it able to
coordinate because of the other things
of the same kind that are doing the same
thing that you're trying to steal each
other's drinking shudders milkshake
alright and you now have history and you
have the failure of all the previous
civilizations because of breakdowns in
those three okay so then let's imagine
the game be groovy coherence version how
do how do we play this let's assume that
the kind of cats out of the bag
people are stumbling and bumbling into
at least transient coherence via more
and less more or less and durable means
these days and that could literally be
site routes at boom festival and
Portugal plus psychedelics is doing
something and there and the whole reason
that there's an even sai-san's
EDM movement I come I can't listen to
the stuff personally but I've heard I've
heard people who have been skeptical
finding themselves in the middle of one
of those dance floors with premium
function one acoustic tunes sound
systems you know and again overlaid with
psychedelics overlaid with large crowds
of people light sound all of those kind
of transformative technologies dropping
into something how what you know how do
we enter this post conventional
communitas coherence whatever it be
without them
moment the kind of the peak of it wears
off reverting back to a game a power
structures in game theory because that's
what I keep seeing I see people
glimpsing it people of being lit up
recognizing it as something new
important magical profound healing
fill-in-the-blank starting to even agree
to organize around it where new family
where tribe we're gonna where were the
frothy edge of evolution whatever it
would be and then the wheels come off
Monday morning when the checks have to
be stroked or when the project you know
the project plans are late or we start
getting back into nitty gritty 3d yeah
so this is what I was trying to say
earlier I'll say it again I think maybe
more actively so when you think about
we've got the concept of game you think
about game a there's two pieces to it or
two aspects or elements one element is
let's just call it society and they're
they're elements here is mind so there's
a particular mind that you're running to
be able to run the code of your society
and society is effective to the degree
to which it has code that works and
minds that run it well okay well if you
delete this oh but you're still running
this yes I've just had my side trance
experience and I've had connection to
the Godhead and what I do immediately
without even a second hesitation as I
immediately began running it on the old
code I am recapitulate in the old code
I'm gonna get the same out no matter
what every time which is you know every
single time you see for example my the
aforementioned individuals who have been
the Kotick or great teachers the past
who studiously didn't write things down
and immediately were followed by people
who did which me became a state religion
which immediately started the process of
killing other people in their name them
it's a pretty interesting story how gay
Mead does that so the first answer is
they wanted the Christ we got Joel
Osteen oh yeah how do you not do this
what's another kind of mind you might
run well okay that's actually a very
tricky question because to think about
it involves invoking the mind that is
not to be to get rid of itself so the
answer is first slow way the down
think developmental right we're going to
actually have to go all the way down to
conception in the developmental pathway
and only do that which is in fact
actually within the coherence that we
have in fact actually have achieved this
is why I said you actually have to go to
that Center and then build out so let's
say you want to say okay we've achieved
coherence and now let's build a an
organization that's like saying I'm a
three-month-old I'm gonna go drive a
race car nope sorry
what can you do maybe you can kind of
have a conversation that isn't going
into game a maybe sadly but development
has a really cool thing you can get
better at it so the first is to actually
really recognize the absolute
irreducible necessity of comprehensively
rebooting mind all the way down were you
saying all the way down down what down
to childhood and infancy like early
childhood development as we do with
conception so Jordan's got infant right
now and we were so he's very much in
that active process of watching and
supporting development we were talking
about the other day I don't know if it's
true or not but there's at least a story
of some Native American tribes were when
they're teaching language rather than
and the kid first starts asking the what
questions what's that what's that what's
that rather than say it's a crow in a
mountain and a buffalo they would say
that is the great spirit expressed as a
crow the great spirit expressed as a
mountain great spirit expresses Buffalo
so their initial semiotic s-- their
initial ontology had the
interconnectivity of everything first
and then the distinction and so when you
say all the way down it's like to the
level of do I identify as a separate
self in my own experience that can get
the design game-theoretic relationship
to you and identify you as other do I
experience that or do I experience some
kind of deeper connectivity in which
synergy is the only thing that makes
sense okay so now we're into an
interesting neck of the woods right by
the way just practically speaking though
somewhere around eleven ten eleven is a
good place that's the level of mind from
like concrete operational on up noting
that you have to also deal with all the
stuff that's going on in the body in
that pre period so if you haven't
resolved childhood trauma or anything
that's going on in terms of even simple
things like bilateral integration do not
the right kind of developmental
environment you're gonna have challenges
you have to actually work that whole
thing that's my conception the stuff
that happens those developmental stages
going back and making sure that the
instrument is in fact a fully
functioning human instrument all the way
up and then of course when you get to
that childhood adolescence phase that's
where a lot of the paradigmatic stuff
starts to begin to layer in and of
course everything that you learn from
17:18 on you should put go ahead and
shelve most of that shelve it in what
way
like don't allow or don't allow it to
make sense of reality from that's the
indoctrination into game a formatting
information semantics yes it's the code
all the code that you've been running
that partitions reality into
prefabricated true and good bits and
bits
yes when you said we're getting
somewhere interesting I want to know
where you want to go yeah it was well it
was specifically what you were
describing as far as you know the
apocryphal indigenous traditions right
that never semantically encoded
separation of self constantly infused
this is a this is this is great spirit
as it you know has annex
rushon and and and you know presumed or
inferred i think is a pre enlightenment
pre rational sense of selfhood that was
actually permeable liminal and you know
this is the bicameral mind if you know
like if that's it that neck of the woods
the idea of hey maybe back in the day
humans no matter how much our Hollywood
movies you know project back 20th and
21st century Valley's underwear sandal
Bible epics you know we actually people
conceived of different cells in
fundamentally different ways their
boundaries of self were more permeable
and they were able to connect in
preconventional collective sense which
actually was the subjugation of the self
and the subjugation of the of serenity
because that stuff hadn't even
necessarily come online in the ways we
tend to think of it then you've got you
know rational French enlightenment
articulation a hyper individual ego
separate selves and then our efforts in
this era say 1700 to roughly now right
the only time is probably the seventies
yeah we've had these we've had fascism
communism cults I mean it was cults and
colonies right that notion of the
subjugation of the self to the
collective and it's at odds with our
value sets and is often been super
problematic so this question is is how
might we other than just growing your
humans which you know I hear you saying
for obvious reasons how might we get to
a post conventional collective coherence
that rather than subjugating individual
sovereignty actually foregrounds it and
pretty to preserve animates it protects
it and at the same time we have that
dynamic subordination or you know not
game theory capture we play well with
each other no one sucking grabs the ring
right and we all create the the Council
of Elrond so you just set up hyper
individualism and some kind of oneness
or collectivism as a thesis antithesis
and you're asking about synthesis it's
one way of framing it
and so far in the conversation for
whatever reason you've been doing a
beautiful job of asking questions but I
kind of want to ask back since I know
this is exactly the center of what
you're focused on how do you see that
synthesis emerging
beats me man I mean I feel like to your
point a little bit like we have to train
we have to practice you know you said
everybody could become a same bull but
like you can't make a soccer team
whether you're saying bow there's only
one of those sons-of-bitches and he's
faster than everybody else
right and so I honest to god don't know
it feels like there needs I mean as as
like I hear what you're saying from the
kind of full-on like Zen Cohen of it
like don't name the thing and on the
other hand if we are looking to migrate
people into at least beginning to
practice it together however messily and
imperfectly what are the liberating
structures what are the rules to the
infinite game right even if baked into
the rules of the infinite game or it's
not the rules either how can we do that
so that we don't have these glimpses of
something more shared between us that
continually seem to unspool and you know
and here's a few that I've seen I mean I
think the key thing is to recognize that
obviously we don't know how because
otherwise we already would have and
that's crucial it's important so it's
worth continuing to try which of course
all of us know intuitively but it seems
important to keep putting it out there
and my sense is at least my own personal
experience is that it's becoming more
clear like I don't feel like I've been
wandering in the desert coming back to
the same place now it feels like
actually there is more and more clarity
so I'll give you some examples of things
that seem to be more right than wrong so
one is let's just take the concept of
learning now what I want to do is I want
to I want to shift and this is not novel
like this happens there's Keats I think
it's key is just to hold things in the
right order the difference between
teaching and cultivating Epiphany
and so teaching is I give you a set of
information I through any particular
means generally rote endeavor to cause
you to be able to repeat that
information back to me and verify that
you've absorbed it in a way that has
high fidelity alright so that is coding
its software and I'm creating some sort
of software mapping in you in
cultivating epiphany I try to find some
how to actually generate in you the
insight they gave rise to that being the
thing in the first place all right so
it's not even teach a man to fish but
cultivate in a man the the capacity of
becoming fisherman in himself fine that
distinction is definitely one of the
distinctions generator function more
than output that's a way of putting it
okay and then we go season now I've got
some thoughts on how to do that
synthesis you said that was one of the
distinctions no I think this this useful
thing of saying hey here's the here's
the stuff I found and you know most of
it has been a disaster but there's a few
that actually kind of work so it's this
let's see what else we got okay so
here's a few we talked about coherence
of difference rather than coherence of
sameness like heterogeneous coherence
correct so when you're talking about the
subordination of the individual versus
individuality there's something having
to do with that there is a
meaningfulness and a beauty and a
dignity of the individual that we don't
want to subordinate in some kind of
homogenizing way we don't want to
decrease the diversity that leads to the
resilience of life
right and then the richness of it a my
own discernment and choice making even
as I'm part of a collective that feels
really important right and then
simultaneously there are kinds of
diversity and difference that only lead
to
unreconciled bol entropic conflicts and
so those are not interesting kinds of
diversity and so we want as much
diversity as we can create synergy
across we get maximum synergy from
maximum diversity with maximum parallax
so now think about for a moment with the
idea of parallax and just just to find
that if it was like so parallax in terms
of the way the two eyes neither eye has
depth perception or peripheral vision
right and when I have both eyes together
they they have a lot of shared things
that they see but because they're in
different locations they also have
slightly different things that they see
so there's overlap a difference right
and this is important so when I put the
two together they're not competing for
which one is right that would be
ridiculous right they're actually the
optical cortex is putting the
information together in a way where if
there's actually an error in this one
it's corrected by what this one's doing
so they error correct each other and
then because I can compute the
hypotenuse of the triangle I actually
get depth perception and periphery so
the two eyes together give things that
neither of them did separately plus
aircraft shape so I want them to have
some shared reality and I want them to
find their shared reality but I also
want them to have difference and then I
want them to relate in a deep way and
then I wouldn't want my ears to be more
eyes right like there's a deeper kind of
parallax between ears and eyes where
eyes are giving me location of things
and ears are giving me a different kind
of location thing so the ears with each
other give me echolocation and the ears
and the eyes together give me a
different kind of sense making in
3-space so we are mr. Potato Head so if
you think about like every imagine if
the ears and eyes were just fighting
over which was right and the other one
was one was comprehensively right in a
complete description of reality and the
other was comprehensively wrong that
would be ridiculous we would dissolve
into gibberish right there is a place
where they all have accurate information
about reality and it's all partial this
speaks to them that initiatives like the
third that you mentioned so in the
context when the relationship between
the eyes in the ears
there's a third we know that third
that's our experience our open vote
yeah right so then the question is okay
eub eyes over years where's our third
but it didn't need about that is that
then you get some very interesting
things where on the one hand you have
both of us actually have a clear
awareness in ourselves that we are here
to with fidelity report what we perceive
of reality we are deeply cognizant of
the fact that that is not reality
we are deeply cogs into the fact that
the other is here to report reality and
that somehow there is something that can
happen that gives a deeper grasp of
reality and the reason when I'm zooming
in on that is that it actually a lot of
the characteristics of this kind of
place have to do with a a way to fully
and deeply honor like all to you
know
without the least bit of attachment to
any of it and that's key you have to
actually we're not in the it's not the
priests the trans so we actually want to
know lots of stuff I want to have really
amazing frameworks we want to have a lot
of life experience I want to bring that
all the way in but then we also didn't
want to have complete non attachment to
any of it and be able to code of create
a bespoke since synthetic language in
real time if necessary okay so that's
kind of interesting I mean I loved all
that okay so I want to add something to
this because this is actually like this
is really exciting to me so I've got
lots of senses right and they're all
taking in some true information they can
all have error and they're all partial I
also have lots of actuator I can move
lots of different muscles and of course
the the leg doesn't want the to compete
with the arm for which one gets to be
the actuator it actually wants to not
just coordinate but to be in a kind of
coherence right and so I've got lots of
sensory stuff I got lots of actuator
stuff why is it that it's not just
random splotches of color
and sound but it comes together into a
coherence of self and world and self in
relationship with world as a coherence
phenomena so how all the sensing comes
together inside of me is a coherence
melena that's the binding problem in
neuroscience right and in the philosophy
of mind and then the actuator why am I
not how do all those parts work together
so well as a coherence phenomenon so if
we think about that every human on their
own the next level up is sensing making
sense and activating but then when we
come together like I want you sensing
stuff differently than I am and I trust
that there is information in that that I
actually really want to have access to
myself and I want the collective to have
and I want you actuated differently than
I am but I really want to come into
coherence so in almost right I mean I
wasn't kind of like that the joke about
mr. Potato Head is actually kind of like
who is the third right if we personify
and your sounds like so we're all
different organs bringing different
perspectives when we come together we
get dimensionality right we get up
whether it's echolocation of binocular
vision we get more out of aggregating
and integrating our realities and that
then becomes as you said not just
fragmented data feeds it becomes a
Gestalt boom though it becomes a reality
for some supersensible
version of us that is greater than the
sum of its parts
yeah
so you said initial conditions good with
novelty and Auntie fragile but what and
then you also said hey the mind that's
running like you take the societal
structure off but the mind the mind that
was formatted to support this assisted
social structure persists even if you
have this experience it's gonna get
looped back through old with
fundamentally gamei habits and patterns
which sounds super fragile this
right like like right now coherence is
highly highly fragile yes and yet you're
also saying it either has an inherent
property or maybe you just hope that it
would be ultimately eventually anti
fragile can we pull that up up because I
think I wouldn't be having this
conversation if it was a done deal
or if the first time people glimpsed it
we're like got it let's go rock
with this this is actually wildly
delicate right now yeah I think this if
you if you hold in your mind the example
the game of game that this happens of
you like the best current example of
coherence and it really is like in the
entire universe as far as we know it by
the best actual example of coherence and
then we say okay well if we do the
Anthropology and we take a look back and
say okay well how long did it take to
pull that together finding the
member I had that spot in possibility
space so imagine a cube and in that cube
let's make the cube 1 million by 1
million by 1 million so it's a big cube
ok and all over there are different
kinds of phenotypes hominids happened to
be a sphere about a thousand by a
thousand by a thousand in that cute
mollusks are down here right inside the
sphere of hominid there's an even
smaller sphere which is homo sapiens
which is maybe five by five by five in
terms of the possibility space and
you're talking sentient biomass what's
your what's your million cube my cube is
the well it's actually an n-dimensional
space but I'm reducing it to three to
make it work so don't put indexes on
otherwise it's go
talk down to the beta for example didn't
exam doesn't does it hold it so the how
do you find in the totality of all the
things that are going on a particular
complex that hangs together to
particular homeostatic autocatalytic
phenomenon that has the thing and
necessary for it to actually hold
coherently all right so what happens is
that there's a lot of different
exploration around this little place
just think of it as a place if you're
not of sapiens right so in hominid you
got primate and you got hominid and you
smaller and smaller in prime in hominid
there's all these sort of explorations
of ok how does this thing where the
different ways to play in this hominid
game and as you kind of get closer to
the the location of Homo sapiens you got
you know homo erectus right and you got
a little heidelbergensis there's a some
things come together but it takes like a
million and a half years to actually
land on Boop there's the thing that
actually has all the different elements
together by the way meta contextual it
has not just the physiological
capacities but it also has grand mothers
and fathers who can actually support the
neoteny authentic necessity for this
plus sista to be able to actually emerge
with culture so there's a bunch of
that's been put together through
evolutionary process it's exploring the
space of possibility and as it kind of
hits there's enough bending of the space
of possibility until orbits around that
spot alright now if you take that we're
looking at something which is inside
that homo sapiens sapiens spot and my
hypothesized by the way has been there
the whole time which just finds a meta
art coming here but we're not gonna go
into TLT ology that is maybe it's one by
one when it's a small territory but we
can notice when so first we can use that
as an example of saying okay this is how
hard it is so we're gonna kind of vector
in that direction and what kind of like
Buddhism will emerge and kind of move
the game forward a little bit and we'll
kind of learn some interesting stuff and
then collapse them Christianity will
happen and look at him do its thing and
a big level up occurs and the general
sort of state of Homo sapiens but we
don't quite get there so now we're at
this point where like all right given
everything we know and given the
timeframe that we think we may have
actually to pull this off what's the
process by which we
explored and of course again the point
that I'm saying is to degree to which as
an individual you can put yourself
inside the sphere that defines this
location you can get there then in that
place can you bring other people into
that place and in that place just that
group what can happen there and this
then the conception metaphor so now
we're moving from the long-term market
the species level is just took at the
long-term are up at the individual level
the fertilized egg is fragile in the
context of once it goes through its
developmental arc extraordinarily
resilient being an adult human is kind
of a kick-ass animal really really good
at being animal but of course the
fertilized egg is still extremely
fragile
so the question when I asked is like
well what's our womb well I'd actually
push back on that I'd say a
adult human this is a is a weak naked
kicked by everybody but with culture
with the instruction manual he's badass
I actually disagree I would point out
that the the things that just basic
humans can do like the Roche it
accurately are actually rather
astounding in the context of the animal
kingdom and the plasticity of the design
parameters with human body can actually
be trained to do that is not coded in
the instinct of a given animal is as
impressive as the flexibility at the
level of ideal space that there is no
Baryshnikov in the animal kingdom and to
the egregious there is the prison to
carve that animal cannot also then
become an Aretha Franklin I think that's
actually pretty intense how much
plasticity in design parameters in this
particular physical body then of course
you layer that plug that actuation
capacity the plasticity of actuation
capacity in with the plasticity of
perception and ideation obviously that
thing is got well it gets you to the
moon and back but I think the the the
proposition that I think you're hitting
on like the key question is recognizing
that the definition or the necessary and
sufficient condition
of coherence that I was describing is
very much the adult form the mature form
and so it is very much the case in my
experience the coherence as it currently
is able to manifest ever ever actually
able to establish it is extremely
fragile and quite difficult to hold
together even in just ordinary
conditions much less than quite
challenging conditions so the the
question of scaling it is a question
actually of how do we simultaneously
increase its let's call it strength its
capacity to maintain coherence under a
wide variety of different conditions its
scope the degree to which it can
actually bring in more people and its
depth the degree to which it's actually
able to fully realize the synergy value
of those people like instead of like a
narrowband
broadband so the question of how do we
scale coherence I think is all three of
those simultaneously if you would if you
mind if we can go back to the initiative
like the little things that seemed to be
seem to be true one of the other ones
that I've found is that most of the
failures to show up seem to actually
fail for relatively simple reasons
having to do with
either the particularity zuv how human
development in world delivers certain
kinds of trauma or the particular it is
about the coming to being of Homo
sapiens delivery what you might call a
species level trauma so either people
who are entering into coherence enter
into relations of codependency where
you've talked about you know the victim
mindset and the savior mindset like
these are all habitual responses that
are either hard-coded into homo
are coded in what humaneness is at the
at the more sort of a primal level or
because we are human beings who
universally have been developed in the
context of society we've developed an
enormous lee large number of blind spots
bad habits and traumas as a consequence
of that so sort of step one of these
sort of you know things that seem to
work is you have to actually gone
through all the work of actually at the
very least resolving yourself out of the
trauma of society to the extent that you
know to pretty high extent to be
perfectly honest and then having a
capacity of being conscious of how
biological instincts and habits that are
hardwired below the developmental level
are going to show up in relationship so
being able to go through that level of
training and there seems to be a kind of
a minimum of those two that Pete anyone
has to be at some level of development
along both those kinds of work to be
able to enter any coherence at all yeah
and so because now we're dealing
obviously there are no folks comfortably
camping out in a happy game be land and
anybody who are going to be the trail
breakers pioneers bridge builders are
going to have to be shedding game a
conditioning and potentially accumulated
traumas and at least but I think you
know we've had some of these
conversations to folks that are breaking
trail and even let's say folks that are
breaking trail and leading the way and
even fairly often bringing others into
experiences of coherence themselves
suddenly too significantly still
traumatize the wounded healers right and
so and even in an instant specifically
we people to come across a community
that's dedicated to working on all those
traumas in fact there's then there's
quite a few there's quite a few that you
know engaging in their access point to
communitas is through helping people
better engage experience catharsis right
and then you get this ecstatic moment of
like holy
yeah we're healed we're whole we're
connected isn't this beautiful and
amazing and then it unspools right there
and the question is like well wait is it
just we need to do more of the thing
that these guys are already doing they
were partial or they weren't quite there
yet and do we get into some puritanical
increasingly high buff or who gets to
play at the coherence game because you
know you're bringing your dirty shoes
into our pure petri dish like how do we
actually help the transitional
generations generations well I think you
already said that key piece so one is
humility the other is patience I think
one of the problems that tends to happen
is there's a real significant meaningful
breakthrough which then takes itself up
set as having been to the breakthrough
oh we did it awesome we're there right
as opposed to a okay this is probably a
three to five maybe six generation
process so it's a more like this this
less like this movement and
directionality with just an
incomprehensible level of constantly
going into humility and recognizing that
no matter how much seems to have been
done we may only be eight percent of the
way there and so that's a lot left and
some since that's that but you can
always get you can get closer and and if
when you are closer this is crucial
right being able to distinguish the
difference between when you are more
towards that unless and then being able
to notice that the choices that are
coming from more towards that are the
ones that should be leading your choice
making
and the choices that are coming from
less from that other one should be
trailing and fading so you actually
become a vector and so that then you
become better and better at using that
sense of more like this that's like this
in more and more of your choices you
actually begin to get a very nice
progressive movement in that container
of humility and patience with enough
runway and enough tolerance for creative
destruction because you talked about
you'd run away
well time Danny because you talked about
like hey humans are amazing and check us
out we can figure out living in the
Arctic in the deserts well not really
you drop any single naked monkey in
either of those places they're dead in
72 hours but right right but but enough
clothes but no cigars and some lucky
bastard finally figures it out and then
that gets encoded in culture and then
not everybody has to die and suddenly
where it desert tribe or where did the
Inuit right so so how do we do this if
right there's both fragility and not in
definite time I am reminded of the movie
the Martian what I notice is that
there's a another trap two traps
actually one trap is the trap of urgency
and the other trap is the trap of like
perceived a responsibility when you say
it's a trap of urgency meaning the
perception and then the acting as if or
do you mean the actual the perception of
the acting as if which is in fact fully
accurate fully accurate perception and
the acting as if is a trap right it's
the it's the notion of you know James
Bond defusing the bomb the clock is
ticking he has to actually be acting as
nonchalant as if he's in the process of
you know swirling his martini because
even the least bit of feeling and
urgency guarantees failure it's the
mountaineering go slow to go fast right
exactly so that's another key right and
this happens all the time as you get it
and now you can see it happen I've seen
that happen many times in myself or
there's a recognition of the urgency
which leads to a certain hardening and a
certain willingness to explain moving
into either things that are not yet
actually possible into here
or rationalizing pulling from the game a
toolkit oh that's a doozy you're done
okay that speaks very much to what you
are saying in terms of people falling
out of their state and we could talk
about what a stage development take from
State experience but we could also talk
about what are the sources of fragility
if we want to talk about antifragility
we should understand the sources of
fragility and what we can do with those
and so some simple constructs if we're
endeavoring to create some kind of
coherence we could have that breakdown
from internal forces or external forces
are both right so external forces means
rival risks type dynamics which is an
in-group that is smaller than everything
given that it is still interacting with
the rest of the world that it's embedded
in so I would say all in groups that are
smaller than everything have some
inherent fragility of that kind then we
can look at dynamics on the inside that
could cause fragility and breakdown
which is actually going into rival risk
type dynamics with each other because
the coherence that brings about the
synergy that brings about the emergent
capacities that actually gets selected
for happens because of a kind of
relating that is anti rival risk it
allows a very deep type of synergy to
occur I'd like to have a proposal meta
and then meta meta move the meta move
I'm noticing that the conversation has a
particular topology to it I'm curious
why that's the case
so it's meta because I presume that the
answer to that curiosity will have
something to do with either homos we are
in fact primates or something about our
developmental environment this causes
topology to choose spontaneously emerge
which is to say that the conversation is
a V Daniel's talking to you I'm talking
to you Daniel and I are not talking to
each other and there is no third
like something right there yeah so
that's one that's the meta move why why
is why did that topology settle in the
way that it settled in then the the meta
meta move they unfortunate oh the meta
meta move is of course in the act of
actually contemplating the meta we can
in fact endeavor to be doing it rather
than talking about it and we can notice
how the doing it informs the talking
about it in a fashion that resolves the
question and in addition to the three of
us and whatever the container or
emergent is this is also on film and
there's the consciousness of the people
who are watching it which I'm also
sensing into and wanting to make sure
that this is hopefully useful for so
that's included in the consideration
something between comprehensible and/or
interesting there's a third to the enth
I mean I I would at least I feel like
there was never been moments little
blips where there's been at least for me
new or interesting perspectives and our
house and insights and I don't know
whether that's things I just haven't
heard you guys say before or whether
those are actually you know imagine that
yes what I'm noticing is that I'm
noticing a feeling that they're not
being something coming from Daniel that
actually creates the right kind of
symmetry in the conversation so I'm
interested in getting your perspective
in a fashion that is not responsive but
is in fact direct like coming from the
inside out
the thing that was feeling to share I
just didn't hear a spot where it was in
it was relevant actually very much
connects to the conversation that the
two of you were having but it was what I
was thinking about anyways which is this
relationship between the subordination
of the individual for the collective and
the sovereignty of the individual like
fractal sovereignty and I was thinking
about the body as an analogy of it's
such a fascinating thing where all of
the cells are autonomous agents governed
by their own internal genetic code they
could grow in a petri dish for some
period of time but they're operating in
a way that is both in their own good
interest and in the interest of the
other cells around them in the entire
body simultaneously so there isn't a
theory of trade-offs of what is good for
them is damaging other or they're
sacrificing themselves for other and
that's tripped the level of cell-to-cell
but it's also true at the level of organ
to organ and organ systems organ system
and cell to organ so at vertical levels
and horizontal levels there's this kind
of just radical anti rival risk synergy
of sovereign things of things that have
their own self-organizing boundary the
facha of the organ the cell membrane and
we're talking about that at the next
level of organism to organism and we've
done that up to tribe and now we're
talking about beyond tribal scale but
that that kind of process and I'm
thinking about cancer in the body
because a cancer cell starts doing what
seems to be in the short-term better for
it it actually replicates it consumes
and replicates faster but it breaks down
the coherence of the whole and in the
process it ends up killing itself
killing its progeny right it suicides
because it debases the substrate that it
depends upon in kind of a short term
small-minded focus
and so there's this idea like regard to
like the there's an interesting feeling
even of that way of speaking of it as
subordinate the individual and I was
just thinking of Einstein's quote that
it's an optical delusion of
consciousness to think there are
separate things when in fact there is
one integrated reality that we call
universe and so like we can actually
rationally get and something I think
about all the time is ok I can think
about myself as a separate thing but
what am i without the atmosphere I don't
even exist what am i without the plants
that generate the atmosphere I don't
even exist what am i without the
electromagnetic field without the earth
without gravity without the other people
that made the things that I use and the
concepts that I use so when I get that
I'm an emergent property of the hole
that has uniqueness and individuality
but it's not separable from that the
distinctness doesn't mean separable 'ti
then I have both distinct and
inseparable simultaneously so I have
interconnected with the whole and having
a unique role to play and so the
dialectic there is something that
increases actually the distinction and
the uniqueness and increases the synergy
and interconnectivity simultaneously and
the first part is to just recognize if
I'm doing the cancer thing it will end
up being bad for what I care about too
even if in the short term it seems like
a good thing and I think that's the
thing with rivalries game theory that
we're at the place where we realize
exponentially larger extraction and
pollution and war an information war is
existential now so we can't even
rationalize that we can keep doing it
that way I'm noticing understand that
I'm trying to get to the feeling of it
which is by the way quite hard but one
of the places I landed was that you know
we still have that nice example of the
jazz band fortunately we actually have
concrete examples of what these things
are like to be in and I'm noticing that
as a player in the jazz band that
feeling of
not being subordinated to the whole but
actually somehow being supported in
achieving a higher level of
individuation is felt so the question of
course was that feel like it's
interesting to notice that while some
people not many I think try to think
about that strategically like okay how
do I make sure that I am in fact
protected
most people are in fact proceeding by do
I actually feel like I am increasing my
autonomy do I feel more agenting and
more autonomous and more able to express
my essence or selfness
into world symmetries like what does
that feel like to actually move into
that place and if we could do it like
what would actually have felt like for
this single cell going into the multi
cell because there's something about the
quality of that that we can actually
grasp at that level you've done it many
times it made different modes like
you've done it when you've gone like
creating a team's doing athletic
activities together so they flow into
something but where the place where each
individual begins to drop into a space
where they are at their peak as an
individual so yeah and that feels like
something you know straight forwardly
obvious which is basically my
coordinators are met and I've seen in my
worldview and everything and and my
needs are validated such that I can then
drop them in order to play you know
going from my five finite game of
separate self into a more infinite game
of emergence and it feels like there
also needs to be a tolerance for
ambiguity and a willingness to get messy
so back to the jazz guys I mean
consistently the most righteous jams
come out of kind of going in down into
the mud as a band you know someone's off
noodling exploring a theme or you know
and it's not actually danceable it's not
anything and it's even to the point of
just unspooling entirely and then some
Quicksilver starlight comes out of that
you know and then it all Joe
and it's that patience to your point
about timing Jordan you know it's the
patience to let it all come undone in
order to come back together in some new
emergent form that seems almost
essential and and I don't know that when
you were just kind of cuz I mean as soon
as you described organisms organs and I
was like oh yeah okay so social media
digital narcissism scraping
everybody else's Jam biting people's
rhymes poaching people's Dhamma feels
like the cancerous impulse that we're
experiencing right now and when we come
when we glimpse this emergence or of
coherence it's sort of like oh you're
you know your life's work and special
like the thing you're uniquely designed
to do you know what in a traditional
sense might be called Dhamma you know
fits perfectly with the thing I'm
uniquely here to do and holy I was
carrying this thing it was lonely it was
hard it was scary it was heavy but now I
think that actually these pieces lay
down beside each other and now we're
actually beginning to see a picture that
none of us held and none of us could see
and that to me is like I think how this
happens but on the other hand we're also
having people be like oh that's a pretty
damn picture let me just scribble it and
snap a selfie and post it well
there's an interesting that happens
there right so as an individual if
particularly the social environment if
you take responsibility in yourself
mmm-me to this right okay so the human
instrument I think has a really
fine-tuned ability to discern the
distinction between those two things so
you can tell when somebody's faking it
in a deep way like something in your gut
is telling you something's off they're
not connected they're not expressing
something that's coming from their heart
all right they're playing somebody
else's jam or whatever the phrase is
that you use if you don't when that
happens if you give that attention if
you give it energy you are up
everything it is crucial as an
individual that on the one hand when
somebody is actually out on the
tightrope in the middle of trying to
figure out how to express something from
the heart that is very
chuckles that you actually call it
that's gold well done awesome and on the
other hand when you feel it no there's
something off about that this guy here's
faking it that you also express that
clearly and so the what happens you
could have very interesting set of
feedback loops to degree to which
everybody's playing the game of both
participant and curator with
authenticity and skillfulness you
actually start getting positive feedback
loops that move into a space that
increasingly anti fragile power but if
there's defection and the defection here
I mean things like laziness or bad habit
or of course obviously just don't
faction defection like oh I'm gonna
steal that and run with it
then it doesn't come together so but
this is this this is nice right this is
fine like two degree to which Jamie you
show up consistently every single time
willing to put it on the line and
calling what is true true and calling
what is false false then and I meet you
there trying to do the same thing what
ends up happening is that we actually
build a relationship that has resilience
to it there's strength to it and there's
strength to it both in the sense that we
can have confidence in it and in the
sense that it can do more than a
relationship that doesn't have that in
it so there is actually a natural like
orientation towards strength that does
show up there but is also based on
skillfulness determined at the bottom to
be a consumer and a curator because
otherwise you got the difference between
Burning Man and fire festival yeah well
this is goes back to that problem of
society so much with discernment is just
like almost the first thing that is
beaten out is discernment and so being
able to come back and do things like
recognize the whole thing here is part
of discernment and being able to listen
and say okay my heart aches when
somebody says something alright well
that's probably real deep important true
learn how to listen to it learn how to
speak what it means with clarity so this
is I came that minimum ingredient
discernment is a minimum ingredient and
in short supply these days and in short
supply but everyone everywhere can
actually improve
the discernment where they are and it
will always make their life better so
it's an easy thing to say increase your
discernment it's never a bad idea to
your earlier call there's actually
something that I feel to add the
conversation that hasn't been spoke to
yet but actually was feeling into and
wanted to speak to the kind of topology
you were noticing because there's a
something that I noticed about I think
is actually really nice so we could ask
is it because Jamie is sitting in the
corner and it's literally just the
physicality of it there's probably a
number of factors but it makes heaps of
sense that you and I have actually got
to have more conversations on these
topics more recently than we have
there's kind of an assumed knowing we
didn't all get to jam before on this or
prepare this this is real-time
extemporaneous and I don't know if
you've ever even expressed Rule Omega to
Jamie but he's just doing it yeah and
he's kind of openly inquiring into the
questions that are really alive and it's
a little bit easier for us to riff off
what each other saying because we've got
some recently shared language on these
things and but the rule Omega is
actually a really simple practical thing
that I towards coherence that I would
like everybody here to get is if if
Jordan mare talking or if you and I are
talking like we we have this and I think
we naturally have it as worth making
explicit is if you say something that
sounds ridiculous to me or batshit crazy
or wrong I actually give the benefit of
the doubt that you might have a reason
that I didn't understand first so rather
than just default into you're probably
wrong ask more questions and and that
giving the benefit of the doubt that you
actually might have something useful to
say increases my making sure that I
understand you before I'm responding and
that actually and the disagreeing was
something that you weren't even saying
because I didn't seek to understand well
enough creates very turbulent flow
rather than laminar flow breaks down
coherence
right if people could just do that
towards coherence if they could just
give the benefit of the doubt that each
other that everyone has some signal even
if it's on a very different part of
reality than the part they're focused on
and even if there's noise involved and
they're listening for the signal first
that would change everything that's a
starting place
so Daniel expresses something and let's
see he's trying to suppose something's
hard which by the way the rule make is
designed for that kind of a thing like
I'm not interested in having
conversations that aren't actually
trying to break new ground so okay do it
dude so you expressing something hard
and in the expression ninety-eight
percent is noise and two percent is
signal like the chance riff but what
happens is that my job is to actually do
two things one hold all of it not just
say that was that wasn't a
hundred percent right so I'm just gonna
nuke it hold all of it
then in my self discernment to what
degree can i express something back that
gets rid of the fifty fifty percent that
is noise so now I've got six percent
signal express it back and of course if
he can then do that
and now you three is even better a more
profound instrument because you're gonna
be bringing a different perspective
perhaps you can take it and actually
zoom in on it down to the point where
actually 50 percent signal that's the
idea
right and so one it's an invitation to
say hey we're trying to do some things
hard let's all try to do something
that's hard to be willing to take the
risk of not speaking elegantly and on
the premise that everyone else is doing
their absolute level best to hear
that which is trying to speak itself
through you and listening in is in
themselves like oh there it is tone got
it there's something beautiful and clear
there here's what I heard and that's
real Omega and there's a psychological
safety that's created to be able to try
out new stuff knowing that we know we're
trying out new stuff and we're giving
the benefit of the doubt so it actually
does become more explorative and that's
where you get more novelty and then I
imagine I don't know if this is true for
Daniel I imagine it's true for you but
certainly if it's true for me is that
I'm also noticing
myself like this constant you know when
you're meditating you feel this this
constant chatter and flow of like all
the things that are going on internally
that are either like certain ideas are
popping up or emotional responses some
of them are like social emotional
responses some of them are like just
like I got a P and like being able to
actually notice all that chatter
internally and do the disturbing
interior and say okay of all that
chatter what's that it's actually signal
oh
but listen to all of it you have to have
you'll make it goes in and out right I'm
listening to myself fully and I'm
listening to the to the others fully and
trying to use discernment to
continuously allow that process to turn
that into gold now there's a really
important distinction that we're saying
something that is different than the way
that some people think about
multi-perspective ism which is we're not
saying I'm not saying all perspectives
are equally valid and I'm also not
saying that there is no way to integrate
them into higher order understanding I'm
saying all perspectives have some signal
generally have some noise and that
perspective is itself a reduction of
information on the reality being
perceived and that's actually quantum
foam of it all from just the definition
actually of observer observing observed
I can't to take myself out of reality to
observe it in a unitary way and if I'm
observing you now versus in a different
state I'm gonna observe different things
right someone else at a different time
if I'm observing the west side of the
house versus the east side of the house
versus the aerial view versus inside the
house they all give me some signal some
truth about the nature of the house none
of them give me the whole truth of the
nature of the house because it's a 3d
object with interior tea in depth and I
can't collapse it perfectly into a 2d
picture right so perspective itself is a
reduction on information complexity so
the first part I give rule Omega to
myself that my perspective has some
signal but I'm also positive it's
incomplete
and thinking that my perspective knowing
that there's truth in it it's easy to
think it's the truth
or it's true with a capital T and that's
like an immaturity we have to get over
there's some truth and I'm positive it's
incomplete and I think there's a pretty
good chance if you've been perceiving
the situation you might have some
additional truth that I actually really
want which means truth is trans
perspectival and Jordan was saying
earlier also transparent attic meaning I
have to take multiple perspectives
through multiple types of interpretation
that was at the beginning saying like
the words aren't gonna quite get it so
we're gonna have to come at it from
different perspectives because the words
are also in a reduction on the
information complexity of the thing this
is also a big part of that what happens
in the post I have it's pre trans you
know what's why is this not a Quaker
meeting the Quakers are doing something
awesome but they're running one paradigm
we have to actually say is okay let's
run what's what the very minimum from
both the Lakota and that quicker
paradigms while we're at it I'm usually
running I don't know 70 or 90 distinct
paradigms simultaneously all the time
and there's many and ie and it is not to
try to collapse them down to a single
master paradigm but actually to allow
each one of them to have the particular
piece that they're holding just like
eyes and ears say okay cool this
paradigm is able to grasp things in a
certain way this one doesn't that's neat
recognizing always that you're never
going to be able to perceive reality but
that by virtue of getting more and more
dimensions of parallax you can actually
have more possibility of having some
insight and it's the insight is the key
not the sense so you're actually going
from sense making into insight which is
very different meanings you're sort of
outside in inside out yeah right that
you're trying to actually build a
capacity to be someone who does rather
than a knowledge you want to understand
know what's happening you wanna be able
to respond to what's happening so it's
you become a musician by virtue of
having a skillful portfolio of
sensitive qualities in self and then a
skillful mapping of that into expression
you don't become a musician by being
very good at reading somebody else's
music so there's something the thing
that I was actually saying that I wanted
to add to the conversation has to do
with the rival risk nature of ego so
like when you talk about falling out of
it the fact that we exist within a macro
economy where we have private balance
sheets and our balance sheets are rival
risk meaning I can advance mine by
ripping your stuff off and vice versa we
have we have structural basis for
rivalry because they involved in a rival
risk context we have to change that so
there's like not just a new sense making
and culture and experience but also new
infrastructure and new social structures
probably beyond the scope of what we'll
get to today
but even we take the balance sheet away
there's the like is someone wanting to
take up more space in the jam session
because of unmet identity needs and do
they actually care about the felt
experience of somebody else who's
seeking to express something and we
actually feel do we actually feel each
other and are we coming from enough
wholeness that I'm not relating out of
need most of the time yeah yeah and
musicians call that cutting right like
it like if somebody deliberately out
plays the other person and leaves that
and leaves their contribution diminished
versus accretive yeah right there's a
cutting sessions and that's bad for yeah
yeah yeah so notice you know if we
switch this domain I'm thinking about
the folks in this side of the camera so
let's take this and make this practical
in the context of sense making in the
world we live in right now almost
everything that we're talking about if
you apply it one of the things that you
notice of course is that all the stuff
that typically goes under the heading of
sense making is worse than useless so
any newspaper any news program pretty
much every scientific paper to be
perfectly frank you know we've done that
analysis isn't taking a look at how a
few of them are replicable
and how much of an incentive structure
there is for actually lying to be able
to generate local selective advantage at
least misinterpreting yeah or
overstating or whatever it's yeah it's a
mess so game a has a sense making
architecture
broadly speaking waste of time well that
opens up some very interesting
challenges alright and this goes back to
the notion of game be being immature
infantile no zygotic haha
but where we are now I would say is
holding yourself a feeling of care for
everything and then truly act and make
sense in the direction of your actual
responsibility which I believe has been
said more elegantly as what does it
think globally act locally
just take that seriously like the
reality is is that everybody's got
plenty of work to do at home and we're
trying well this what I'm saying what
I'm Ryan articulating is that to do this
thing to come into coherence to play
game be there's a lot of work that has
to be done in the individual in yourself
and then the way to learn how to do
coherence is always going to be with
people with whom you actually have real
relationships not us not some three of
us your wife your husband your kids your
parents or at least other human bodies
with whom you can actually be in real
physical proximity meaning for a
meaningful amount of time so that's
that's definitely going to be the fabric
out of which this thing gets woven it
takes time for sure and it takes doing
the hard human stuff so you actually
have an embodied experience of what it
feels like to actually do the hard human
stuff as opposed to book-learnin on that
direction and good instincts and good
habits built through long practice and
the notion is to say Oh Chris connect
the dots the proposition is if you want
to actually resolve problems around
immigration in Italy honestly not
to make yourself feel good or to look
good to other people but for real then
the path to get there is this path that
starts here in yourself and moves out in
spirals through things that you can
actually touch and truly take
responsibility for and then always
showing up from that Center of
sovereignty mm-hmm so that feels like
hero's journey 101 or Dorothy in The
Wizard of Oz right well you're saying
hey the way forward into Game B and
emergent coherence is to actually come
all the way back home to the basics of
good old-fashioned humanity but in order
for me to be able to reanimate and fully
live into the basics of good
old-fashioned humanity I actually have
to have gone on some initiatory
transformative journey in order to
remember in fact that cow town
in Kansas is the best place ever and
there's no place like home
nice so you just joined I get it and
we're adding those two together it comes
clear beautiful yeah yeah that's very
nice it's very it's actually odd how
simple and like plain things are and of
course what's interesting is once you
grasp that once it lands you begin to
see how the the bigger challenges begin
to self resolve there's a point you made
that wasn't the main point it was a
tangent but I think it's super critical
so I want to emphasize it which is okay
so why can't we trust any of the things
that normally look like sense-making
well there's a bunch of reasons but
basically we learn how to do signaling
for intentional game theoretic purposes
and so rather than just share signal
that is true and representative we share
signal that will advantage some
rivalries agenda so most signal ends up
being that and one of the things that
you were just saying is a consequence of
it is that there's an ethic to not
up the information ecology right like in
the same way that we say don't pollute
and most people get pretty comfortable
and don't throw your cigarette butt on
the ground
don't actually dissing form anybody else
for your own getting ahead or withhold
information where you can avoid doing so
because you're actually disempowering
the sense making of others in the
process and to really be tuned into as
though as I'm seeking to make sense I
want to increase other people's
sovereignty in their capacity to make
sense so I want to increase the
intactness of the information ecology
they're exposed to rather than decrease
it right up to but not beyond the point
of bostrm and those guys info hazards
yeah-oh to the degree that someone else
has clearly rival risks agenda with
regard to information then you have to
factor that in so far as sharing
information with them within decreased
sovereignty for lots of people but glue
together what Daniel said and what you
just added to what I was saying to the
degree which I'm playing this game with
complete strangers out in InfoSpace well
never meet I'm probably gonna lose I
don't have my how much info info playing
which game the game of will Omega the
game of information ecology cuz
multipolar traps someone's gonna be a
dick she agrees I'm playing with my wife
I'm probably gonna have a better life so
that's the idea yeah it is if you're
playing it trying to say okay hold on
I'm trying to solve the game theoretic
problem with complete strangers by
telling the truth
anybody who had interests chance how to
do came through he's gonna say oh you're
the one who's actually the dupe we found
this up don't be med stuck don't pinhead
stark unless you're actually in
Winterfell with your family then be Ned
Stark that's the idea right don't the
key is don't go to King's Landing .
that's the key the sensor to your point
though if you're saying hey yeah you
know honour information ecology for the
enhanced sense making of all - the folks
will do the multiplayer polar trap grab
the ring capture the flag but in a rain
in a realm of infinitely distributable
digital information aren't we always
simultaneously playing both of those
games at once
without even clear understanding of the
which and the when and the who that's
when this thing has got to go away
unfortunately this sort of the remember
I said the inverse is and the current
sense making environment I have an
expectation that I should simultaneously
be aware of everything that's going on
in the world and a sense of my having
responsibility for it you just pointed
out the media infrastructure that
supports that possibility has a
catastrophic collapse around it so
bizarrely enough the only way to have a
prophylactic sense against that
catastrophic collapse which we can
double-click on it that's not clear what
I mean by that is to only have your
media infrastructure be driven by direct
real relationships so begin with real
relationships and proceed from there
lots of problems with broadcast but the
ability to amplify dangerous and wrong
memes and to be able to share without
context and without relationship and
without connection and without relevancy
and without being able to speak into the
capacity for listening and if you just
come back to the body for an analogy
cells go cancerous the body's dealing
with them all the time right you'll you
only get cancer if the body can't deal
with it but imagine if a single cell had
the ability to broadcast its message to
every other cell simultaneously and it
didn't have to go through propagation
through the cells surrounding it and
those types of things like we'd be
instantly we the kind of key
thing that's helpful is that each cell
is being modulated by the cells near in
to come back in to check and so there's
error correction processes okay
so let's unpack that because so for sure
you said hey think globally act locally
but that doesn't scale fast at all
you talk about developmental processes
patience that stuff doesn't meet
timelines and then we discussed the
notion of the moment you go to some form
of politics of suspicion effectively
right and and the idea that there's
esoteric exoteric you
the secret with an inner sanctums outer
sanctums those kind of things I think
that's clearly worked in the past for
any you know ultimately infinitely
potent linear traditions and the kind of
those sort of things there's there with
its filters and gates of who had access
to the information in our unique
contemporary situation taking the
example like Sasha Shogun right so the
chemists who you know re popularized
MDMA created a lot of you know design or
molecules compounds and psychedelics and
then was collaborating with the DEA and
then when the DEA looked like they were
going to be shutting down and repressing
that information published his two
cookbooks where he open sourced I said
this big thing about open sourcing
versus closed source and he opened
source all that information now net
positive on the world but if we use him
as an example if he went the open source
route
now you also ended up with street corner
chemists being able to do things they
never would have Anila do without his
two books published you also ended up
with the advent and rise of and popular
promulgation of psychedelic therapies
did Sasha do the right thing should that
have been kept and cloistered and how
does the notion of coz I mean the thesis
of stealing fire was the only shot we've
got to avoid weaponization
commodification or collapse into
hedonism and particularly the first two
are just better funded better focused
they're gonna beat our asses every time
is to open source reliable techniques of
self initiation effectively right and
ideally in service of coherence faster
than efforts to capture it and I don't
know whether that's true and I don't
even know whether that's wise but that
was the best idea I had at the
time so like what did we think about
that because you could say just dump it
all out there publish it let the chips
fall and hope that the Rebel Alliance
right somehow hangs on to the plans for
the Death Star ahead of the instead of
the empire building even better desktop
what I was thinking as you're saying
that was Lou tick she's dead metaphor
while the stuff was going through me as
you were as you were talking and one of
the things that came to me was
I feel reasonably confident that there
are in fact things that are appropriate
to being open source we actually
mentioned one earlier discernment so
discernment is the sort of thing that is
somehow now just uncapturable it's anti
capturable so two degree to which
somebody actually goes to the process of
building their discernment they are in
fact more likely to become an ally than
they would otherwise have been for
example and so the Rebel Alliance
shouldn't be building or outsourced in
our open sourcing plans on building
Death Star's they should be building an
open sourcing plans on how to build a
Rebel Alliance so that if the import
what about lightsabers hold on it's just
so if the Empire gets a hold of the
plans all that happens is the Empire
becomes more Rebel Alliance unless
Empire
so not lightsabers not lightsabers this
is this is actually really tricky topic
one relevant concept is the concept of
safe to fail probes and so in you were
mentioning earlier that the people who
went into the Arctic like probably most
of them failed and then some small set
figured out how to make it and then
those are the ones that figured it out
right so and the same with the jazz riff
where it's mostly gibberish but some
beautiful thing comes evolution it has a
very high fail rate but it's exploring a
wide search space and then the things
that make it through are awesome right
and one of the things you're asking
about timing is can we do an
evolutionary process factoring the time
that we have and can we keep allowing
failure with exponential failure
possibilities and so the CDC open
sourcing everything that it knows about
bioweapons would be stupid because on
one hand you could say well it's cool
that they're open sourcing the knowledge
so more people can work on protecting
against it except you actually have more
capacity for that knowledge to be
harmful than to be beneficial and with
bioweapons or with anything that can be
weaponized at that scope with AI with
nanotech with you really have different
considerations
because you can't really control safe to
fail probes and say so say that again
like justjust phrase that a different
way if the worst thing that can happen
is your jam isn't that good like that's
not that bad
it's a bummer and you the next thing you
have a better Jam if the worst thing
that happens is you release a
autopoietic pattern replicator that
kills all life you can't around
with like playing with that thing and so
you you actually have to be much more
careful that if anyone is exploring how
to create antifragility to that
knowledge that should be held carefully
okay great so labeled so how do we say
hey let's just imagine that we have with
a little bit of thinking let's say we
could woodshed you could fund you know
whatever 24 rad and McArthur level super
smart folks to come together and come up
with protocols for group coherence that
work more often than not do we open
source that or are we more concern that
it can also build the Borg well if I
double-click on the content of that the
answer is it we open source that but
that's because there's no such thing
underneath it the do such thing which
has protocols for group coherence
there's more along the lines of remember
it's we were trying to cultivate insight
not teach so it's there's a way to
generate a in individual humans the ins
the embodied insight to be able to in
themselves build a capacity to come into
coherence that then does actually come
into coherence so if you were to be able
to again the sermon ISM is the canonical
point the open source determine great
open source practices and techniques
that work in the directionality of
improving discernment at the individual
level but I want to go back to something
you said earlier because I think this
ends up being quite key you mentioned
something that about the like the path
of
relationality doesn't scale well for me
with the addition of how a
supersaturated solution does it phase
transition to crystallization that I
think is the answer if you actually do
this thing where what your your field
effect which is to say your open source
broadcast is bringing more and more
people into a poised state where their
ability to move into coherence is
becoming easier and easier and easier
then when as up happening is that a
small amount that actually does drop
into coherence creates a crystallization
phase transition that could actually
scale extremely rapidly and has the
characteristic of being very strong and
very precise because it's starting on a
basis that has no compromise yeah I
think we're actually I mean it depends
on how we're defining coherence and what
you're what you're perceiving as initial
conditions okay and your question about
states and stages basically because it
feels like you're emphasizing a stage
based argument which is that it's slow
it's hard work and you have to really
grow and develop into the person that
can stay really hold coherence and I
think what I find notice what I'm
tracking I'm like yeah absolutely that's
the foundational level the springboard
from which you leap and obviously the
higher that is the less hops you gotta
have right to get to the level of
coherence and between you know smart
tech pharmaceuticals
you know lineage practices like there's
enough out there these days that you can
for sure create at least you know like
the vomit comment you can create moments
where everybody is weightless you can
create a a transient group coherence
that and there's it's a bell curve
distribution from what I can tell 10% of
the people lose their don't know
what to do with that space or you know
in maybe it's like 10 it could be more
but like to say tails you got you got
the people who
and lose their and then you got the
people it doesn't budge at all and those
are the psychopaths and they should not
have been exposed to this and then
there's the bell curve in the middle who
were like oh wow you know the Omega
principle like oh wow
I'm an organism I'm in here I'm an AI
holy we're seeing in parallax this
is joyful wondrous amazing
transformative and so what do we do with
that I'd like to enter topic we haven't
talked about yet which is the what Trust
is to coherence it was mentioned earlier
not defecting and so one model that I
just used personally for trust is I
trust people as much as I trust them in
their worst states yeah yeah because if
there's a bell curve distribution on the
states of behavior they're gonna go into
maybe which is for most people pretty
coupled to their emotional states
unfortunately right I want to uncouple
those so that even if someone's in a
shitty emotional state they don't behave
shittily that they can witness it and
not act on it right like I'm in the
fetal position right now no smashing and
crashing things right and then I want to
help what makes them go into the
shittiest emotional states which is
trauma and meaning making patterns I
want to help heal that right so they
don't go into a shitty States as often
but then also decouple their internal
state from their behavior but if if
someone mmm sometimes takes information
I share with them and uses it in really
synergistic ways and generally it is at
least discerning but when they're pissed
off uses it as a weapon against me but
that happens
well I can't share certain things with
them right so there is raising the floor
of the shittiest behavior you allow of
yourself in relationship that makes you
more trustworthy that is actually really
at the heart of our ability to have anti
fragile coherence
that says you know what no matter how
upset with you I am there are certain
of things I'm just never going to
do as my own standard for myself and
then part of our discernment is to also
be able to pay attention to where
someone is not just in their highest
states after the state induction methods
you're talking about but where they are
in the shitty parts and one of the
things I'm really interested in is not
just making people's highest state's
higher well what brings them into their
shittiest states is still anchored and
now they they actually have a wider
space to reconcile and they can even get
bipolar about it it happens a lot yeah I
want to help clean this stuff up for
sure and it's recursive I was landing
there as well I was thinking okay so
state and stage obviously for me the
first thing that comes up in terms of
state is there's the constant recurrence
of the trap of taking the state for the
stage all right so let's carefully
partition them and say okay they're not
and to the degree to which you've gone
to burn him in and take taking drugs you
are not in fact actually else anywhere
but maybe you saw Michael imps that
there is somewhere else to go that's
neat
so very carefully so the first is big
red flag state is not staged the state
is not going to get you to stage by
itself take it slow okay so then what
happens in state and as I was kind of
just again for some first-person
experience well a lot of the stuff that
we were talking about in terms of what
given individual has to actually be able
to come into to be able to start
participating in a direct collaboration
and getting to stage in my experience
actually happened in States I you want
to try to heal trauma trauma healing can
happen very well with say psychedelics
art of transparent mind really really
effectively supported by certain kinds
of ecstatic states so there's a lot of
things I think I think if you actually
take the state and think of it as an
instrument they can be pointed at
particular capacities that can be moved
into stage because or through the use of
that so how do I use a particular state
experience to actually develop men to
the level up a stage in my personal
development and just have iterations
there then I think we're good then I
think it works very nicely but we know
where the center is
here we want to develop mature human
beings and there are many many different
state experiences that are part of the
process of doing that many of which we
have to use now because our
developmental environment so us
up that we're gonna have to use some
pretty interesting tools to break stuff
out yeah absolutely
I mean that would be my sense as well
it's just that they are it is a
beautiful thing that a peak state that
creates safety security connection
insight belonging can lend itself very
strongly to to be the fuel source for
deep anything we see this with MDMA PTSD
therapy and a bunch of other things but
it basically allows you to go back and
reformat and reintegrate places that are
currently wounded or traumatized and
that we do that in relationship with
others tightens trust tightens bonds and
then further creates the capacity for us
to learn to play well with each other
through all those stages which you know
surfacer if we can learn to share states
well with each other and experience
momentary coherence momentary
transpersonal sense making and be in in
the in the mud with each other
supporting each other you know that in
the the linkage between those two is the
community oz is like you know to me it
feels like this you know nothing new
Under the Sun kind of but like if
you think of like gospel churches you
know coming out of the African American
slave experience it's like there's that
sense of they are perfectly designed you
know vehicles for a lot of this which is
you sway you impact you do you guys
sealant that the trailer for the new
Aretha Franklin Amazing Grace so it's
like this she did this ripping album
called Amazing Grace in a Watts Gospel
Church in like 1974 and then all the
footage was lost and it's just come out
like I literally wept seeing this this
trailer was unreal and she
starts singing the song Amazing Grace
and she just takes that a and she just
does her she goes all over the she's
like 29 years old at the time and but
but the Gospel Choir who's backing her
up are like giving it up like they're
feeling the shimmy shakes they're
feeling the juice they're giving it up
for and then they stop praising and
testify
like the whole thing just goes through
the roof and you're like oh my god and
then there's the swaying the clapping
the dancing the movement and you're like
it is weeping for the humanity of our
wounding it is praising you know the
divinity of our possibility and it's
connecting like literally like church as
a vote and you're like ah man we
got it you know we see the dust that
off and like create new versions I
mean when you imagine the gospel church
one of the things that makes it so
powerful is that you're also noticing it
is in continuity with a bigger context
it's actually part of a real community
right and so it's not like you teleport
to the Gospel Church and then you all
fly back to your different cities you
walk out and then you go live with each
other and it contains the whole of
humanity it's got little kids and
grandmas it's got grandpas it's got the
whole human family in a single place so
it's kind of like a heuristic if your
state experience is you and a bunch of
other 20-something rich white people
it's probably not right something's
probably off about that there's
something gonna be missing if it
contains the whole of humanity turistic
right not ideology heuristic this you
know it's a and you know across
different a whole community if it's
continuity if the group is spontaneously
getting together in bali and then
everybody's flying back to their West
Coast East Coast
flyover cities again probably not gonna
get the thing done if on the other hand
you're already living in community and
the state experiences supporting a
deeper communitas that is lived 24/7
okay that's more likely to work so it
sounds like you're adding state stage in
place enduring enduring continuity
wholeness all right think of it think of
it as part of a whole continuous process
and then of course what happens is you
get all kinds of interesting stuff
because now you know one of the things
as your particulars you're talking is
likely this really interesting thing
like okay what are the failure
conditions in the efforts to go here
again like where does it fail and one of
the ones was really interesting is like
the difference between makalah gluing
together analytics and true synthesis so
gluing together analytics is this thing
we're like okay I've got one piece trans
paramedic of mine I've got another
pieces that I've worked really really
good in my yoga practice to be able to
feel peaceful I got another piece where
I've taken a whole lot of drugs to get
this a bunch of people so we really feel
close and we work some stuff out of her
over ayahuasca and then I'm gonna do is
kind of like put these in the same space
and pretend that by sticking them
together really hard I've actually
achieved some new synthesis in fact what
I have is I have three distinct things
that aren't actually actually integrated
so it's the difference between a puzzle
and a photograph or even a puzzle and a
real piece of reality and I think we're
into this a lot it's almost like the
group equivalent of spiritual bypass
which is that we can arbitrarily
generate a simulation of eating each of
the artifacts of coherence and we can do
so so consistently and so effective with
it we really do think we've actually
achieved coherence like do you feel it
yeah I feel it me do you have
transparent mind I'm got it no problem
like every piece every piece that you
can identify you can show and yet it's
not the whole thing because it's
actually not integrated into a
continuous wholeness so that I think is
something to be very careful about is
that you can't stitch it together it
actually is coming from the direction of
is this actually part of an integrated
wholeness with these heuristics you know
do I notice that there's a whole of the
human family the whole human tribe a
community a real community is the state
experience connected on both sides with
living this that kind of stuff like I
think there's a lot of really good stuff
that can be done using those heuristics
and preventing the failure conditions
unless that hope your grandmother like
does it grill corn does it grow corn
right can it produce children who grow
up to be good kids right that kind of
stuff and of course the point there is
that because that gives you a check
something you know if you're evolving in
a simulation of coherence but you can't
actually resolve just basic stuff in
yourself but you can always just
teleport back to New York and have your
basic stuff nobody notices anybody can
fake it from 60 days but if you actually
have to raise children together okay
reality is going to tell you whether
they actually deliver on the thing yeah
there's a grow corn hope you grandmother
nice I'm stealing that oh they say one
of the interesting things in a world
where the market has subsumed almost
everything
is the difference between production and
extraction has become unclear most
places and so someone can do well
financially without actually growing any
real corn by manipulating markets by
manipulating marketing financial
services are mostly that type of
phenomena marketing is mostly that type
of phenomena and so someone can have a
false sense of being a success that
their ideas work because they're
financially successful though they have
been net in tropic to the world their
work has actually been net entropic
that's actually that whole notion you've
been describing you've shared that with
me recently I've been thinking it ever
since you first said it but the idea
that wisdom has been subject to kind of
I don't know what the exact phrase you
use like captured by the market yeah
can you speak more than that because I
mean obviously you're talking you were
talking about discernment and you're
saying hey if you want to show it and be
a good person and just that right trust
the omega principle but not everybody
else is playing that you're undone yeah
and then you've been thinking through
even the signifiers of wisdom they're
available which would hopefully increase
people's discernment how gone tits up I
mean Jordan mentioned earlier when he's
talking about take a teaching from Jesus
or from anyone and then see what game a
does within it when it becomes like how
the teachings of the guy who emphasized
forgiveness became the basis of the
Crusades and the Inquisition is like a
really great example like how the
did we figure out how to do that and so
there's still a similar thing that
happens when if someone makes their
living by sharing wisdom and they're
able to split test optimize the nature
of what wisdom people respond to the
most and what persona expressions and
they can click optimize and they can
even just allow Facebook's algorithms to
click optimize the version of wisdom
expression that it lands the most you
get a capture of wisdom by Rivals games
and this is the kind of we have to
be like really honest with each other
about and honest with ourselves about to
create an information ecology that
doesn't have disinformation
in it because right now like if
true information about reality is a
source of competitive advantage within
rival risk games and I both want to
withhold true information and I want to
dis inform and I want to miss signal you
slow down there say all that again
because that last two senses this felt
like important if true information about
the nature of reality
is a source of competitive advantage in
a rival wrist game I know where the
water is and you don't but if you go
toward the water hole is you'll it
up for me or whatever it is then I want
to not tell you where the water hole is
I also want to dis inform you and tell
you that it's somewhere else so you
don't accidentally find it I also want
to maybe exaggerate the specialness of
my knowledge so that I become the only
bearer of water or whatever it is right
so we have insu not not back to you but
just to some other potential consumers
right right so your this is potentially
like rival RIS supposed wisdom keepers
against each other I mean there's the
kind of unwashed masses to which we flog
and it doesn't even have to be that
conscious and intentional right it
simply happens in the nature of I want
to get this message out there well this
version of it is more acceptable and it
gets out there better and right so then
there's this kind of multipolar trap
degeneration of the content to be
susceptible to broadcasts and
susceptible to mainstream ability of
premature focus on scaling in which case
split tested analytics and and then what
that means is I'm compelling people to
listen which is the opposite of
supporting their sovereignty I'm
actually figuring out causal
psychological manipulations to
manipulate their choice to do the thing
I want them to do rather than try and
support the sovereignty of their choice
making yeah it's a pain in the ass but
we have to like every single time we go
to the like when you think about these
kinds of problems you at least for me I
keep coming back to the same basic place
so obvious is a prophylactic against
this entire thing is just you know
broadcast my and as soon as wisdom is in
fact just lived relationally it's why
that's why landmark is bigger than the
pasta right I mean they've gone they've
gone they've diluted to the lowest
common denominator they've made no bones
about putting people
exposed vulnerable states and upselling
and living up yeah it is
transactional yeah there's gonna be
problems if it's broadcast there's gonna
be problems I just have to speak to it
irony of us talking about this on
broadcast
fortunately three white men specifically
within about roughly the same age I
think we're actually the same person
well I think the beauty of what's
happening though is that it's so
unlikely that anybody's actually going
to watch this video because it's so
incomprehensible and just hard to follow
that it's it's actually not a problem
the with Tinchy answer is kind of
thinking about that in terms of like the
meta is to degree to which this is
actually interesting at all what I would
say is that this is genuinely just a
conversation this is I mean for those
who happen to be watching this is
straight-up just exactly what a
conversation as up as that is
what we talk about and this is no
different as far as I can tell I mean
I've had conversations are both of you
in some conversations the three of us
together I mean me a little bit more
formal but not a lot I think was a
slower start up like we cut it there was
a little bit of that's right we didn't
jump into it but this is more or less
just water conversation with us is like
so but your point I think is quite quite
nice okay cool so what do we do
heuristics like how do we actually
prevent this from creating unintended
negative consequences so here's
something I wanted to enter in that I
didn't yet and this was coming in it
from a completely oblique direction of
anything we've talked about so far but
it has to do with what the motive for us
doing any of it is for doing any doing
actually and so it has to do with the
nature of desire and this is something I
I find really fascinating if you look at
the beginning of if you look at Buddha's
Noble Truths and desire as the source of
all suffering and as kind of a essential
Eastern teaching and then you look at
desire as the cause of passion and
creativity in Western teaching there's a
really big dialectic between those
that's kind of worth
navigating and there's some deep
ontology as to why and why I model those
differences and so in a Western model
made in the image and likeness of the
Creator be creative and desire is the
source of the imagined more beautiful
rich future for us to be creative right
Eastern model it has us disconnect from
the fullness of the moment to imagine
that a future moment could be more full
and it actually makes us feverish and
up and then when we get it we're
only happy for like a moment and then we
want something else
Eastern model focused on being which
happens in the moment Western model has
a model of time that is reified focused
on doing and becoming which is fulfilled
in the future and so of course I'm only
happy for a moment that I want something
else because becoming is actually what's
relevant becoming more and more full one
way I think about this is if I think
about desire as like voltage right like
a pressure or a gradient for flow a
basis for movement I can think about the
low gradient inside of me in the high
gradient in the world some some lack or
emptiness and myself that creates a
desire to get something from the world
get recognition get money get sex get
attention get something right and I
think that Buddha was right to say that
that is the cause of or at least related
with suffering and it's kind of like to
the degree that I am affirming a sense
of self that is in lack I get more of
that sense of self to those who have
more shall be given to those who don't
have the little they have shall be taken
away biblical quote but we're having is
like a state of experience a state of
consciousness so then there is a
different kind of desire that is not
just no orientation for movement which
is an inner fullness that actually has a
imperative to flow into the world so
there is a desire and there's a basis
but it's actually coming from wholeness
not from unholiness is that Molly Bob
Marley like my cup overfloweth and I
don't know what to do yeah how Fez this
poem I become this beggar has become so
rich that my biggest problem that was
empty
my emerald filled pockets into the world
quickly enough and so there's if I'm
coming from that place in the jam
session
I can totally just let you Jam if you're
in a meaningful place if I am coming
from the other place and I need to be
seen then I'm going to cut you off to
make sure that I get seen or make sure
that my lick was the best or something
like that and this is where the
identities that are still seeking more
and then can feel less in comparison to
each other is the basis of rivalry that
creates the fragility of the coherence
mm-hmm yeah it's such an interesting
thing like the yeah I agree with you
that that teaching is which is say
useful and works that there's a way to
actually recognize that you are capable
of being full with simply yourself
there's no need to have something from
the outside to fulfill but rather
through doing something in self and then
when you're in that place ah this is
actually very similar to what you were
talking about when you talked about the
the least city to the most to the when
there is a high low there's actually
okay a way of developing self so as to
be able to even when the interior the
self is actually lacking in some way
still to relate to that as full because
the reality is is you don't actually
need that much very very little really
minuscule amount really particularly in
contemporary environment and so there's
a disposition that can be achieved which
is nice like there's a disposition that
allows you to then be in a relationship
where that gradient form desire is not
have much traction it does not pull for
me at least I can constantly feel it
there's a pole but does not have much
pull and I should mention by the way for
me at least the training has also been
having a noticing when it's going to
build I'm thirsty now okay well I better
take care of that that actually is
something that needs to be an actual
conscious choice to satisfy I need now
this is the
thing with your focus on sovereignty and
starting at home that is so critical is
because if I'm not tending to my own
wholeness I I actually can't do any of
the stuff we're talking about right
exactly and then and then what happens
is in my experiences that is that every
human being I've ever encountered is a
cup overflowing provided we're resourced
right so my sense would be is that is
that you were describing some element of
like well if you're Buddha writing
you're completely understanding and
you're purely coming from being you've
integrated that relation the constant
you know dialectic between being and
becoming then that's how you play the
game but like you were talking about
culture architecture and how do we
actually get humans in culture and in
game a with all the traumas of life how
are we helping us you know walk each
other home then I just keep coming back
to that ocean notion of you know that
gospel church which is the idea like if
we can have momentary provisional
transient experiences of coherence right
Church you know the Holy Ghost feeling
right and we can use that as metronome
oh yes I was off the one and now I'm
back on the one right I remember
and a tuning fork oh I was banged and
scraped this week but man I'm just like
you know I've sweat my prayers I've done
whatever I've done and then training
wheels now I'd like MDMA therapy right
now I feel resourced I feel love I feel
connection I feel coherence and now let
me go and it might lost me the next hour
it might lost me all a Sunday it might
lost me to hump day who the hell knows
but I get a little further each time
practicing so rather than just we got to
do a whole bunch of hard slow grooming
up to develop to the place where we
might finally get to start practicing
can we do these in parallel type of gig
and a:hover talks about that like well
which is it
you know the tops down bottoms up gross
you know anything it's both because
that's how life happens and if but if we
and I'd feels to me like the peace that
socially we're missing the most these
days to your point about Bali and but
you know transformational culture is
that people that really good at the atom
bomb peak experiences these days they
can blow up sky-high their
they're terrible at the other 360 days
of you the simple stuff yeah and right
sleep right you know like at a daily
practice and like even like a revival a
meditate corrective Sabbath elective
that tone the bell yeah yeah I've
actually I noticed it's such an odd
thing for me is that I grew up in in
Texas in the 70s so where prayer at
mealtimes was actually very commonplace
but my family didn't practice that so I
had this experience of like what the
heck is that and this was when move into
secularism and even the New Atheism was
becoming part of the cultural fabric so
as would is that and also a little bit
of like that's not cool alright and as I
got older that actually kind of
disappeared but I've actually noticed
over the past what maybe even four years
I've actually been to build a prayer and
mealtime practice myself but from the
inside out meaning that it's not formal
it's not imposed I'm not like we're just
reciting a script that I've learned I
haven't learned it rather I had an
insight which was oh well there's a lot
of basic practices like feeling deep
gratitude that are crucial and you
always have to eat yeah so I would
always forget to have my gratitude
practice but when I said you know what
I'm gonna do this before I eat I'm gonna
do my gratitude practice I'm just gonna
bind something that just has this really
cool characteristic of being really hard
to forget
ie eating with something that's really
useful and has a little bit of cultural
Vectren just combine the two and then it
just began to expand from there so this
is of course the recreation of ritual it
is also part of the story yeah and
that's a lot of culture hacking we can
do right I mean I mean grace gratitude
at dinner Shabbos you know Sabbath day
down a down day every week to reflect
and reset like these are simple things
that are easy to dust off and reanimate
and I really think again I think there's
a lot that can be open sourced we just
have to make sure that we're not open
sourcing the technology we're open
sourcing the technology to
and bring into insight so don't open
source the info open source things that
build developmental capacity the
generative process led Tampa so when you
said you didn't come back to prayer
because you were deciding to adopt the
tradition but you discovered that that
made sense
yeah and earlier you're talking about
education that is not teaching info but
that is facilitating Epiphany yeah when
someone has real epiphany and they
figure out something that's useful and
then they teach other people and the
other people don't understand why and
that happens a few generations the
Dharma becomes dogma right like the
thing that that had real wisdom just
becomes a thing to do because the
authorities told us and then liberation
actually looks like rebelling against it
and even if we're submitting to it we
don't really get the gist and so to not
have Dharma become dogma and become a
control system it has to be alive and
real and rediscovered for everyone and
that's a different process than an
emetic transmission exactly the medic
transmission well what about a catalytic
mimetic because that has to be a lot of
good syllables doesn't it sound like no
truly I mean what would to your point
about your you're giving your to your
disclosing and the protocols for self
disclosure that that could arguably be a
catalytic them principles more than
protocols mmm-hmm yeah yeah no more I
mean I'm interested like we're even a
mythopoetic catalytic mimetic so what is
the story of how we begin to remember
and it's going to have to be again more
in the direction of poetry or the
parable of how we begin to remember so
that it's hinting to people in
themselves moments in their lives but
they have in fact come across stumbled
across or opened into beginning to
remember such that they can find in
themselves the thread that is there is
that they can begin to follow with
greater clarity mmm-hmm yes and then I
can testify by the fruits right and then
we have to be very mindful of the fact
that you this is what the twelfth
done we've kind of gone through this
cycle on who's counting which we got the
axial age we had the Christian Islamic
era we had you know we have a series of
points where there's like okay guys
here's a whole new level up you know
somebody has an epiphany they have a
real epiphany it's for real and they're
like all right this time it's not
turning to Dogma guys let's get it right
the trick of course here is that we kind
of have to okay so this comes to what
you were saying earlier that I wanted to
comment on I'm gonna say something that
will sound like really inspiring or
depressing or ridiculous I'll go with
ridiculous go so I'm gonna speak
mythopoetic ly about the space that we
read we've talked about it like this
before is that exponential tech the
technology extends the power of our
choice making and but our we have tools
that give us the ability to make better
tools that give us the ability to make
better tools so we have an exponential
curve it's just been very slow and now
it's not very slow now it's in the very
quickly compounding place and so we're
getting exponentially larger levers on
our choices but we're not getting
exponentially better choice making and
so we are getting the power of gods
without getting the love or wisdom of
gods to wield that power that's a
self-determination scenario I don't see
any scenario where we don't get the
power of gods that seems eminent and
unavoidable and so they're really like
there really is this enlightenment or
bust thing that I see which is if we
have catastrophic level tech not just
isolated two state actors but they can
be radically decentralized who gets to
be totally up nobody or even not
be very Omni considerate to can do
catastrophic stuff on accident so this
is like the existential Bodhisattva yes
it is this is the bodhisattva imperative
actually has to become universal for us
to make it through this phase and that
wasn't true in the Bronze Age or Stone
Age or Iron Age
the other ages because we could just
kill a lot of people we could destroy a
lot of environments and we did now it's
just kill everybody in all environment
right so let's then jump back to the
story I was trying to tell earlier quite
poorly so zone of proximal development
we've all got that notion right that
there's a place we could get to now
let's think about them the level up from
Homo habilis to homo sapiens and the
many many different things that all had
to come together simultaneously for that
zone of proximal development tool and
you had to have yet Yatta knee and
grandmothers and fathers and the
emergence of the capacity for language
and a certain affinity to not beat the
out of other males as soon as you
can counter like a whole bunch of stuff
each one of which independently isn't
necessary particularly useful and any
one of which is lacking it the thing
doesn't hold together very well right so
you've got a bunch of like little micro
versions and if they don't that don't
work and they fall apart until
eventually get to the zone of proximal
development and then pop it kind of pops
together I was thinking about that in
terms of oK we've we're in this place
for all right we're making another run
at it we're trying to get we're trying
to get to this spot and the question is
well was what are the pieces what are
the pieces of the puzzle and I was
really interested in like noticing that
we've got a whole bunch and they come
from lots of different places you know
you mentioned the Quakers and the Sioux
and we've talked about like Buddhism has
stuff like non-attachment
like one of the interesting traps for
example I was thinking through in terms
of like okay if I had an epiphany and I
want to share it and it turns to Dogma
one of the reasons when in terms of
Dogma is attachment I want people I'm
attached to the good word and so some
interesting things about okay what's the
toolkit what are the pieces of this next
stage that if they come together they
mutually support each other like the mat
that when people stand in a circle they
all kind of like turn and they begin to
sit down simultaneously
we're just perfectly as you begin to
lose your balance you sit and you land
on somebody else's knees and it goes all
the way around the whole circle like
what's that thing where all the pieces
come together and the stage now has the
elements that support each other so we
actually have reached a new place
and what I notice is this this really
interesting thing where like if I
applied non-attachment
and humility by the way which are really
interesting cross products if they're
coming from very different Latin
lineages and they reinforce each other
quite nice so say them again
non-attachment and humility in the
context of urgency and in the context by
the way of we've done a lot of
conversations about the if you really
really think clearly about the
circumstances that we find ourselves in
even just the simple construction daniel
did of as you're becoming more and more
powerful as you become unlike and to god
in the direction of destructive capacity
if there's not an equivalent like unto
god then in level of wisdom and care
you're likely gonna things up real
quick and we've been through this many
many times there's every construction
you go through leads to the fact that we
really don't have that much leeway we
don't have that much time and the number
of paths that are not in fact
catastrophic are extremely narrow okay
well hold that that's true
hold that hold the energy and the degree
to which that creates a motivational
push to cause you to just do stuff that
is hard at the same time have both
humility and non-attachment yeah those
the and committed at a level of
intensity that's like way up there and
not attached like that's the stuff that
moves you to this point this singularity
where the pop happens and the stage
settles in yeah this is the being doing
dialectic being grounded in a being that
is actually full means unattached to
needing fullness from the doing
achieving a particular thing and yet
like a way i think about it is there's a
fullness of what is but i stopped
thinking about reality as a noun and
think about it as more verb like i can
have a fullness with what is and they
can also recognize an evolutionary
trajectory i can recognize the beauty of
life and be nourished by it and i can
also know that it's mine to add to the
beauty of life as best i can
and that's being appreciating the beauty
of life doing adding to the beauty of
life becoming increasing our capacity to
be and do at greater depth
rebel wisdom is a new sense making
platform bringing together the most
rebellious and inspiring thinkers from
around the world if you're enjoying our
content then you can help us make more
by becoming a subscriber which will give
you access to a load of exclusive films
also you can then join our group zoom
calls to discuss the ideas in the films
and you can send us ideas for questions
for upcoming interviews we're also
looking for talented people to help us
out with editing graphics music that
kind of thing and if you're a regular
viewer you'll know we talked a lot about
the value of embodying or actually
living out the ideas that we talked
about so that's why we run regular
events in London check out the links on
the website for more and hope to see you
soon
you